<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Art of cuckoldom, or, The intrigues of the city-wives</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11675319</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11675319</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 8:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Art of cuckoldom, or, The intrigues of the city-wives</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 96 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Frontispiece is a portrait of "Alderman Whittington afflicted with the gout".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48097:1"/>
            <p>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>eighteenth century engraved portrait of Richard or Dick Whittington with a cat</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Alderman Whittington</hi> afflicted with the Gout</head>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48097:1"/>
            <p>THE Art of Cuckoldom: OR, THE INTRIGUES OF THE <hi>City-Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48097:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48097:2"/>
            <head>THE Art of Cuckoldom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>INTRIEGUE I.</head>
               <p>THERE was a very pretty young Virgin Gentlewoman, whoſe whole Patrimony was her Face, together with a very handſome competency of Wit, the bounty of Nature on one part, and a genteel Education beſtow'd her by her Friends on the other. For to tell Truth, Providence had not been over generous in any other world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Capacity: Not but that ſo much Beauty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a fair and ample Fortune, ſuitable to her other Accompliſhments, and indeed ſhe was Born to ſuch a one, had not the over pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs of a prodigal Parent (her Fathers ſower Grapes) imbitter'd her unlucky Circumſtances, and thereby intail'd ſome Frowns in the World upon her, her forementioned Education being indeed the whole Portion ſhe had left her.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48097:3"/>
               <p>This young Lady a little turn'd of Sixteen, (an Age that generally furniſhes the fair Sex with ſome little ſpeculative Knowledge into the great Work of their Creation, the End they were Born for,) felt an extraordinary Paſſion for a young Gentleman on this ſide Twenty, a very zealous Adorer of hers; and one that (not to render the conquer'd Virgin a Prize too eaſie) had fairly Sieged her Heart, and had as nobly won it.</p>
               <p>But for another Perſecution of Fortune; this Gentleman a younger, or rather youngeſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of not an over-Rich, though otherwiſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Family, had as little to truſt to, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the unkind World as his Miſtreſs. For as ſhe had only her Eyes and Charms to raiſe her Fortunes in it, ſo he had little elſe but his Sword to raiſe his; a Commiſſion abroad, or perhaps ſome Court-favour at home, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the whole Foundation of his Hopes.</p>
               <p>Theſe unhappy Obſtacles to their Felicity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duly conſidered, eſpecially on the Ladies ſide, (not but ſhe lov'd him to a hight, even to run all Hazards for his ſake;) ſhe durſt not, or rather would not Marry him, out of a principle of pure Affection; as well remembring an old Proverb, That <hi>when Poverty comes in at the Door, Love creeps out at the Window;</hi> inſomuch that, that only Check, <hi>viz.</hi> Her loving him too well to run the riſque of loving him leſs, reſtrain'd her Inclinations from ſo dangerous a puſh as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48097:3"/>
               <p>All Things being thus duly weigh'd, ſhe took an occaſion one day with her kind Arms round his Neck, and a dropping Pearl in her Eye, to burſt out into an extravagant Complaint againſt the cruelty of their Stars, that ſuch true Love as theirs ſhould be excluded from the Bed of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>Marriage:</hi> That ſhe was intirely his own, her Love, her Life, and what not. However, ſhe cou'd no ways conſent to a long miſerable Life, (for that wou'd be their Nuptial Portion) only for a few ſhort liv'd Bridal Joys—with infinite more tender Expreſſions upon this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Subject.</p>
               <p>The young Lover who in all his Paſſion for ſo darling a Miſtreſs, was ſtill Maſter of ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo, cou'd not but acquieſce in the Juſtice of her Complaints and the mutual Reſentments of both their Misfortunes, under this cruel Bar to their Felicities.</p>
               <p>Some little Time after it happen'd that a very eminent Merchant in <hi>Lime-ſtreet,</hi> of the reverend Age of Fifty Eight, was Captivated with this young Fair One; a Man of a true City Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, Naturally very Jealous, and as Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Covetous, being a Perſon of a very low Extract, though otherwiſe bleſt with the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Smiles of the World, having heaped together more than double an Aldermans E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p>This ſuperannuated <hi>Inamorato,</hi> being now entred into the Rivals Liſt to our young Gallant, makes his bold and open Addreſſes to the fair <hi>Phillis</hi> (let that paſs for her Name:) For though
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48097:4"/>the diſparity of their Age might have rendred him a more modeſt Intruder; Nevertheleſs, as Wealth never wants Front, the conſideration of that ſingle Advantage ſo amply atoned for all other Imperfections, that well knowing his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments that way, he accoſted her with all the Courage of an Heroick Lover.</p>
               <p>This new Victory was no ſooner obtain'd, but her firſt <hi>Io pean</hi> was ſounded in her young Gallants Ears: She immediately run to her dear <hi>Strephon</hi> (for ſo we'll call him) big with the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of ſo doughty a Conqueſt as her new <hi>Lime-ſtreet</hi> Captive. As formidable a Rival as his City Figure might make him; nevertheleſs, ſo anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated a Pretender to ſo young a Bed-fellow, created no great Jealouſies on the young <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Side. But to ſhorten this heavieſt part of our Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, the young Lovers in an Amorous Conſult between 'em, come to this Reſolve, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Man of Gold ſhall carry the Dame: She ſhall Marry our grave Citizen, and her contented <hi>Strephon</hi> wear the Willow. However, not to make a too mortifying Divorce between the young Lovers, 'tis agreed; that the Virgin Prize, <hi>viz.</hi> The Firſt-Fruits of Love ſhall be <hi>Strephon</hi>'s, and the old Gentleman ſhall only be admitted Tenant to her Reverſion. In ſhort, ſhe'll condeſcend to make a City Husband of one, and a Court Friend of the other; the good old Gentleman, the titular Lord of the Soyl, like old <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſhall ſhower <hi>Gold</hi> into her <hi>Danae</hi>'s Lap, and <hi>Strephon</hi> ſhower <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48097:4"/>
               <p>Accordingly all reaſonable Advances are made on her ſide, to her Small-Ware Merchant, her <hi>Lime-ſtreet</hi> humble Servant. His Addreſſes are favourably heard, his Suit received, and the Preliminaries ſoon fettled for the great, and now eaſy, Work of Conſummation; eaſy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, for the happy <hi>Strephon</hi> has opened the Blooming-Roſe, done his aged Rival that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that the Bridal Night Drudgery, is not like to be too hard a tug for his Fifty eight. Thus whilſt all three Parties are rapt up in equal Felicities, the young Wantons in their ſubſtantial Joys, and the old Fondling in his imaginary <hi>Paradice,</hi> the nuptial Day and the bridal Robes are all fixt and prepared: Our <hi>Strephon</hi> and <hi>Phillis</hi> having firſt Sworn an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable Correſpondence, the Golden <hi>Fleece</hi> to be at his faithful Service, as often as 'tis poſſible to lull the watchful <hi>Dragon</hi> to give 'em the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</p>
               <p>To paſs over the matrimonial Ceremony; for indeed 'tis little elſe but Ceremony; at leaſt on the feminine ſide: After ſhe has received all the congratulary Compliments from the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent City Matrons, and took her Seat of Honour amongſt them, ſuitable to the Dignity of the fair Partner of Magiſtracy, the Bride of ſuch an Honourable Metropolitan-Member; After her firſt due proviſion of all Perquiſites of State, Equipage and Grandeur, equal to her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; The next and indeed moſt important Study, is the performance of Covenants with her dear <hi>Strephon,</hi> for as to her Vows at Home,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48097:5"/>ſhe left them at the Altar. Love is reſolved to make ſtrong Work here, whatever Cobweb Lawn it makes there.</p>
               <p>But now under her nuptial Yoke ſhe ſees a great part of her Hopes defeated; 'tis almoſt impoſſible for her to find that happy Minute of meeting her <hi>Strephon:</hi> For her doating City Sir Politick is ſo fond, or at leaſt ſo cautious of ſuch young Fleſh, that he is never out of her Sight. 'Tis true, ſhe keeps a Coach, but ſhe can never go abroad in it, without his Luggage to load it: If ſhe pretends to go to Church, he is in earneſt with her there; and whatever Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhe prays to, he reſolves ſhe ſhall never be upon her Knees without him. If ſhe pretends a Viſit to any Relation of what Degree or Sex ſoever, 'tis a downright Affront to his Years and Perſon to be left behind her; ſo that ſhe muſt either carry him along with her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe goes; Or, plainly tell him, ſhe is either aſhamed of him, or has Deſigns upon him, which is neither conſiſtent with her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nor the great Game ſhe has to Play; for the Hope of a Rich Widowhood will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to put any Slights upon him, leſt it might endanger his Death-Bed good Graces, and a kind laſt Will and Teſtament. In fine, it was a full Month (which Lovers call an Age) before ſhe could have one half Hour with her dear <hi>Strephon,</hi> and that very difficultly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p>What uſe was made of the ſhort Minutes, the Reader may gueſs. But more particularly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48097:5"/>they laid this Plot together, that her Spark being of a perfect Beau ſhape, fair Complexion'd, and as yet wholly Beardleſs, he ſhould Dreſs himſelf in Womens Apparel, and by paſſing for a dear Country ſhe-Cozen of hers (to whoſe admiſſion it ſhould be her Buſineſs to pave his way) he ſhould be received into her Houſe; and by Living under her Roof, have all the private Hours of ſtoln Delight, that their own Hearts could Wiſh. This Deſign ſo well laid was decreed for ſpeedy Execution, the Lady equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with a fair Yellow-lined Purſe (a ſmall Token of her brighter Golden Favours in ſtore) to furniſh him with all the Feminine Accoutre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments requiſite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly, about Six Days after, by which time the young Spark had not only rig'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>Capapee</hi> for a <hi>Virago,</hi> but alſo practiſed ſome neceſſary Graces in his Looking glaſs, more cleverly to carry on the Maſue; and likewiſe his kind <hi>Phillis</hi> had rapt up her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Spouſe into wonderful expectations of a viſiting Cozen of hers ſhortly look'd for in Town: With this preparation the bonny Laſs makes her Entry into our Alderman's Roof, with all the welcome Reception imaginable. Her-Lodging Apartment is immediately very Reſpectfully, and no leſs Prudently provided, being a large Room on the ſame Floor, only a Stair-head between that and her new City Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen's the Alderman's Bed-chamber. By this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick freedom how many riotous Joys were taſted, though no ſet Feaſts of Love, but only
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48097:6"/>ſo many running Banquets (a ſnap and away) may eaſily be imagined. However, as our <hi>Phillis</hi>'s whole Extaſies were all bounded in her <hi>Stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phons</hi> Embraces, it was a little ſhackle upon her Delights, to think that ſhe could no ways fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh out more plentiful Revels, <hi>viz.</hi> A whole Nights Regale in thoſe darling Arms. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the two Lovers contriv'd a very pretty Stratagem to gain that Enjoyment. For which purpoſe one Evening by a ſmall ſlight of Hand ſhe conveyed a ſmall quantity of Jallop into the Alderman's Supper-broth, which Operating as ſoon as ever he came to Bed, the poor Man was forced to riſe ſeveral Times in the Night, which unſeemly miſchance made him ſo aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as well as ſurprized at the ſuddenneſs of the Indiſpoſition, that with a kind of a Bluſh, to have ſo tender and Nice a Stomach as his young Brides offended by ſo unſavory a Society, as his at preſent is; he deſired her to make bold with her Cozens Bed for that Night, whilſt his Servants ſat up with him, and ſome learned Aſſiſtance was called from abroad to take care of him.</p>
               <p>The poor young Lady with a great deal of Tenderneſs for him, and paſſionate concern at this ſudden Irruption, was very hardly preſt to deſert him in this Condition, till his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Commands compelled her to withdraw: and accordingly, ſhe trips over to her expecting <hi>Strephon,</hi> where we'll leave her to as little Sleep as her ſick Man ſhe left behind her, the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of warm Love on this ſide affording as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48097:6"/>little time for Reſt here, as the Jallop does there, 'Tis true ſhe has the Misfortune now and then to hear ſome unmuſical Gruntings and Grumblings, from the tother ſide of the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, a very melancholy Diſcord to her tender Ears, had not ſome ſweeter Harmony in her <hi>Strephons</hi> Embraces a little ſoftened thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful ſounds, together with the private Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation of ſo ſucceſsful an Intrigue.</p>
               <p>All Matters thus go on rarely: This raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Night on the young Lovers ſide has eaſed a great many hideous Sighs and Longings, now all amply ſatisfied by this favourable occaſion. In ſhort, not a ſhadow of Suſpicion diſturbs their mutual Joys. Nay, not only the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's, but likewiſe another younger and more penetrating Rival's Eyes are deluded by this Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Maſque of the happy <hi>Strephon.</hi> For I had forgot to tell my Reader, that our <hi>Phillis</hi>'s Charms had captivated our Merchant's elder Prentice, a young Spark within Three Months out of his Time, and by Birth a Gentleman, a very accompliſht Youth; who to tell the Truth, from the firſt Day of his Maſters Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, had not only entertained an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Veneration for his fair young Miſtreſs, but likewiſe naturally imagining that ſuch dry Bones as her old Husband, could not be over-extraordinary ſatisfactory to ſuch young Veins; had one Day aſſumed the confidence to Breathe a few paſſionate Sighs to her, and to throw himſelf a perfect Adorer at her Feet. 'Tis true the Fair Offended gave him but a cold Anſwer,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48097:7"/>and perhaps repremanded him very ſeverely for ſo bold an Attempt, againſt ſo much Virtue and Honour, as could not but be highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned by ſuch inſolent Language. However, this Repulſe had not wholly daſht him; but that he both continued his Devoirs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not wholly deſpaired of a more ſmiling Beam, that might one Day ſhine a little warmer upon him; not at all doubting, but as louring an Aſcendent as her rigid Virtue yet held, that ſtill ſhe was Fleſh and Blood, and that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fond Hony-moon of her cold Fifty Eight, would not laſt always.</p>
               <p>As prying a Hawks Eye as this more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Critick might have upon her; yet ſtill, as I ſaid before, neither our young <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Behaviour or Deportment had any thing that in the leaſt look'd like Maſculine; ſo very art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully was the fair Impoſture carried on.</p>
               <p>One Afternoon a little time after, it fell out, that the young Lady was called to a City Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, an eminent Neighbours Labour. And as this particular occaſion gave her the freedom of going abroad, unhaunted by her trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Perſecutor; ſhe whiſpered her dear <hi>Stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> in the Ear, that as in all likelyhood ſhe ſhould return pretty late in the Night, when the good Man would be aſleep, ſo in Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him, ſhe was reſolved at her return to ſlip to Bed to her dear Cozen, upon pretence that at ſo unſeaſonable an Hour, ſhe was afraid ſhe might hazard the Waking him, and ſo break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Reſt.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48097:7"/>
               <p>The fair Cozen to make all due preparation for ſo dear a Bed-fellow, took the occaſion that Evening to pretend ſome ſmall Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo went to Bed a little ſooner than ordinary, with a deſign to have taken a ſhort Sleep before hand, to be the better Fortified for thoſe ſprightlier waking Hours ſhe ſhould have occaſion to melt in Raptures after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>The young <hi>Strephon</hi> having thus bid good Night; it fell out that a young Girl a Neice of the old Gentleman's, that lived ſomewhere towards <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> a very honeſt poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe whole Fortunes depended upon her rich Uncles gracious Favour, came to pay her Duty to her honourable Uncle and Aunt, the Aunt being at that time abroad, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that part of her duteous Devoirs yet unpaid, the old Gentleman reſolved ſhe ſhould ſtay all Night, as being uncertain of her Aunts return. And not to make any Ceremony with making another Bed for her, by way of good Husbandry and ſaving that trouble, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make bold with his Wives Cozen's, who was juſt gone to Bed before; being withall charged that ſhe ſhould diſturb the young Ladies Reſt as little as poſſibly ſhe could, becauſe ſhe was gone a little Indiſpoſed to Bed.</p>
               <p>The poor Innocent Girl, without any more Attendance than a Candle in her own Hand to light her up, accordingly prepares for Bed, where entring very ſoftly, ſhe finds the young
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48097:8"/>Lady faln faſt aſleep, and therefore in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to her Commiſſion, the Bed being large, and the young Lady lodged on the further ſide, ſhe pulls off her Cloaths and puts out her Light, and creeps very ſilently into Bed, as cautious of Waking the ſleeping Lady.</p>
               <p>By this time the whole Family were all gone to Bed, excepting a ſmall Domeſtick that waited below for the return of the Miſtreſs from her Chriſtian Viſit abroad. The young <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter</hi> Laſs was no ſooner in Bed, but, what by Virtue of a good Supper of ſomewhat better Fare than her own Commons at home, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Fatigue of a long Foot-walk from <hi>Charing-croſs</hi> to <hi>Lime-ſtreet,</hi> was faln into a very ſound Sleep. At this time the young <hi>Strephon</hi> waking, and his roving Arms being the firſt Member that moved, he felt a ſoft Bedfellow lodged by him; hereupon being not only Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported to find his dear <hi>Phillis</hi> ſo near him, not Dreaming a Miſtake, but likewiſe hearing by her Breath, that ſhe was faln aſleep, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his impatience for the unutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Joys, however he was reſolved he would not Wake her too rudely; and therefore firſt gently ſtealing his warm Hand into her Boſom, the ſoft Temptation ſoon grew ſo powerful, that he could not forbear rambling it a little farther ſtill, to which her ſound Sleep gave him all the free Acceſſes his moſt libertine Fancy could reach. Theſe preliminary Bliſſes having now intirely fired him all over for more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Extaſies, he could not forbear claſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her round in his Arms, when with thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48097:8"/>burning Kiſſes ſealed to her Lips, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancing her ſo cloſe, her Face happening to lye towards him, and not ſo much as the leaſt Bar between the neareſt touch of all her ſofteſt Chrams; (for his own roving Hand before had removed and unveil'd all interpoſing Skreens) theſe too ardent Arms about her, and ſome other yet more ſurprizing preſſure ſo very near her tendereſt Virgin Treaſury, the poor Girl was immediately ſtartled out of her ſleep, into that hideous Terror, that ſhe preſently ſhriek'd out, crying, <hi>Help, Murder, Help, I am Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd, I am Ruin'd;</hi> and ſo leapd' from him out of the Bed, the poor <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Amazement no ways hindering her flight (for the change of the Voice ſoon diſtinguiſh'd his fatal miſtake, and put him into no ſmall Diſorder and Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.) This uproar of the poor frighted Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den alarm'd the whole Houſe, inſomuch that not only the Husband from his Bed, but likewiſe ſeveral of the Servants from theirs (particularly the Elder Prentice we ſpoke of, who run down from his Chamber above in his night Gown,) all bolted into the Room where the poor Girl, under little leſs Apprehenſion than downright Raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtill continued her Outcry; when her Uncle asking her waht was the Reaſon of all this noiſe, <hi>Oh Sir,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>you have put me to Bed to a Man, a filthy, lewd, wicked, laſcivious, wild Man. Lord have Mercy upon us,</hi> reply'd the old Gravity, <hi>a Man! Yes Sir,</hi> cryes the young thing, <hi>this impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent pretended Neece of yours, is a</hi> He <hi>Devil in Petticoats, a meer</hi> Tarquin, <hi>a downright Ramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Limb of</hi> Lucifer.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48097:9"/>
               <p>Juſt in the height of all this diſmal Outcry (the poor <hi>Stephon</hi> being little leſs than Thunder-ſtruck, and having only time to leap out of the Bed, and skreen himſelf in a large Night Gown that lay upon the Table,) it happend that the goſſiping Lady was juſt returned home too, and entred in the nick, full in the middle of the whole hideous Impeachment againſt her poor diſcover'd Sham-Neece, to her no little Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Confuſion. However with a little more Preſence of Mind, and ſomewhat a larger Talent of Aſſurance than the poor mute <hi>Strephon,</hi> ſhe fell very Magiſterially upon this clamorous young Roarer, and askt her with what Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhe durſt talk at this wild rate, or what Bedlam Frenzy had poſſeſt her, to run on with all this Noiſe and Nonſenſe? <hi>Nay Madam,</hi> anſwered the Girl, <hi>dont think to fright me out of my Reaſon; what I ſay is Truth: I ſay again, and again, 'tis a Man; and though I thank my Stars, I am a pure ſpotleſs Virgin; yet I am not ſo Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant at theſe years, but I have my feeling about me, and know what's what, Madam. And if I had not had Grace enough to cry out as I did, but been as willing as he, I might have been Raviſh'd before this time. In ſhort, if I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a Spindle from a Wheel, or a Peſtle from a Mortar, or any thing in this World; nay, if there be a Cock Sparrow in all the Hedges between High-Gate and Hamſtead, or a Whoremaſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Aldgate and Weſtminſter, I tell you once more, this impudent She Cozen of yours, is a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right He Rogue, Madam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48097:9"/>
               <p>Before the Lady cou'd make anſwer to this crying Charge againſt her dear <hi>Strephon,</hi> the old Gentleman took up the Alarm; <hi>She Cozen! with a Pox,</hi> cries he, <hi>Any, I am He-cozen'd and She-cozen'd too in the Devils Name; betwixt your Ladyſhip, and your Ladyſhip's Neece, I am ſweetly brought to Bed, I thank you; I have nurſt a Snake with a Sting in his Tail indeed. Yes, you Jezabel, with your Mr.</hi> Horner <hi>in Petticoats, I have been finely Cornuted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before the poor Lady cou'd ſpeak in her Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (as indeed it was but a very barren Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) the poor Elder Prentice, who by this time had fully ſmelt the whole Intrigue, and ſaw his dear Miſtreſs in this inextricable Plunge and Labyrinth, very generouſly fell down uypon his Knees, beſeeching Pardon both from Heaven and his Maſter, when his own Guilt and Confuſion muſt unravel this whole Myſtery of Iniquity, and unfold the whole Riddle that had occaſion'd all this Alarm and Diſtraction: And hereupon with a great deal of Pentience and Shame, he very formally told them, That he himſelf was the true and only <hi>Tarquin,</hi> the intended Raviſher, that the young Woman had accuſed, and who had made all this wicked Aſſault upon her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Innocence, and that by an unahppy, tho' no leſs guilty Miſtake; for what through the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Devil, and his own Brutal Luſt, he had a long time conceived a Deſign upon the Chaſtity of his Miſtreſs's fair and vertuous Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, and this Night intending to put his wicked Purpoſes in Execution, he had ſotlen down
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48097:10"/>from his own Bed to ſurprize her in her ſleep, and not knowing of this Stranger's being Lodged with her, through the darkneſs of the Night he had miſtaken his Prey, and only through his Beſtil violence, had been the whole and ſole Author of all this Diſturbance. And though at the young Gentlewoman's firſt Out-cry he had leap'd out of the Bed again, and ſtole back into his own Chamber; yet his own, now too ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing Conſcience had made him return to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his intended Villany, and implore all their Forgiveneſs. The old Man who had ſcarce Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to hear out the Story, notwithſtanding the ſatisfaction it gave him in clearing his dear Spouſe's and Cozens' Innocence, nevertheleſs cou'd not forbear a great deal of very violent and opprobarious Language againſt his wicked Servant for this outragious Fault. But his good Lady, who by a private wink to her kind Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, had partly acknowledged his wity and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Ingenuity in this defence of her endanger'd Honour, very modeſtly reprimanded her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's too vehement Indignation. She told him, That truly ſhe had as much, or more Reaſon to be angry than he, for her Virtue and Reputation lay at ſtake; not but her Cozen, if occaſion had been, ſhould have ſtrain'd a Point of Virgin Modeſty, even to a more ample Demon ſtration of her true Sex. But as Heaven had been pleaſed to clear the innocent without any ſuch unſeemly proofs, and the Criminals true Penitence had made ſome part of an Expiation for his Fault, it was their Chriſtian Duty to endeavour both to forget and forgiven.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48097:10"/>
               <p>All Parties being thus fully convinced, and all Clouds intirely diſſipated, the fair She-cozen (was likewiſe graciouſly pleaſed to grant her Padon to the penitent Offender, for now we may reſtore her her feminine Epithite) declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That ſhe was heartily ſorry, that ſhe ſhould carry any of thoſe fatal Charms in her Eyes, as could have power to provoke any ſuch lewd Attempts againſt her Virtue; not but had the young, too Violent, Gentleman addreſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her by any Modeſt and Honourable Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Paſſion towards her, perhaps upon fair and virtuous Terms, ſhe might not have been wholly inſenſible nor invincible.</p>
               <p>All Things thus huſh'd, the good old Man took his harmleſs and ſpotleſs Lady to his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, and his <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi> Neece lay down again by her late Raviſhers ſide, who took care to play the <hi>Lucrece</hi> not the <hi>Taquin,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Night.</p>
               <p>The next Day our fair Gueſt, took an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to take her leave of the Family, in order to her pretended return into the Country, out of a Point of Virgin Honour, as not ſeemly for her to remain any longer under that Roof, and ſo near that Perſon by whom ſuch Violence had been only offer'd to her.</p>
               <p>Though her <hi>Strephon</hi>'s abſence was highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretted by his dear <hi>Phillis,</hi> yet ſhe was forced to conſent to it, as not willing to have ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Spy upon her Actions, as the Rival Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, who ſhe was now ſatisfied was no longer a ſtranger to her whole Maſquerade. However ſhe comforted her ſelf, that this dangerous Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48097:11"/>had not above two Months to ſerve, and then ſhe might have fairer Liberty for her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd <hi>Strephon</hi>'s ſafe return again to her Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces.</p>
               <p>No ſooner was the falſe Cozen and true <hi>Stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> departed, but the poor bluſhing <hi>Phillis,</hi> out of a principle of Gratitude, took an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to make ſome farther acknowledgments to the kind Prentice for her protected Honour in that unlucky Exigence. To which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, That truly as he had had the Fortune to relieve a Diſtreſſed Lady, he hoped her Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Smiles (for he was ſo far mercenary) would be pleaſed to reward his Service: And now if he was ſo impudent a Beggar, as to ask a return of Love from her, however the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch a Petitioner was ſo far excuſable, that the niceties of Virtue cou'd be no Bar to his Ambition, and nothing but her Averſion, cou'd deny him that Bliſs. To conclude, he preſet the Subject ſo home, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her vow'd Fidelity to her dear <hi>Strephon,</hi> ſhe cou'd not tell hwo to refuſe him: She was Conſcious to her ſelf, that her Frailty was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and (if for no other Reaſon) ſhe ought to conſult the preſervation of her Honour, by huſhing the Silence of the Diſcoverer, though at no leſs price than her laſt Favours; beſides the Merit of the Service he did her, in ſheild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both her ſelf from inevitable Ruin, and her dear <hi>Strephon</hi> from eternal Expoſure and Shame, demanded her kindeſt Retaliation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Invaſion of her <hi>Strephon</hi>'s Right, was at leaſt in this Caſe, a venial Treſpaſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48097:11"/>
               <head>INTRIEGUE II.</head>
               <p>AN Eminent high City Mercer, much ſuch another doughty Yoke-mate to a young Bride, as our <hi>Lime-ſtreet</hi> Merchant, having much in the like nature, taken <hi>To have and to hold</hi> a wet Eel by the Tale, call'd a Wife, a Girl of high Sanguine, juſt on this ſide Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; was Conſcious to himſelf, that his natural Abilities ſtood fairer for a Deputy of his Ward, than a Family Duty-man at Home; having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed over-match'd his reverend and ſuperannu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Manhood in the Choice of a Spouſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though ſo fair and fruitful a Soyl, was but weakly and poorly Till'd at Home, he took all the neceſſary Care to keep off all Foreign Hands from the Plough, as reſolving to have it lie Lay, rather than bear any Crop but his own; and accordingly made all the Fences to ſecure it, that Caution and Safety cou'd invent.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Place, he debar'd her all Viſits Abroad, without his own Perſonal Attendance. Secondly, To keep her from Sloth and Idleneſs, the general Nurſes of Wantonneſs and Vanity; he introduced her into his Buſineſs in the Shop, her Station behind the Counter, being her ſix days Labour; ſo that from Morning till Night
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48097:12"/>ſhe was kept imploy'd; This Projection carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a double advantage along with it, as being likewiſe a promotion of Trade; for ſuch lovely White and Red within Doors, is a greater at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of Cuſtom, than a gilt Sign without Doors, the Town Gallants being always invited to buy their rich Mercery from ſo fair a Hand.</p>
               <p>And Laſtly, To guard all ſafe at Nights; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Chains and Bolts, and all the Iron work of his Doors, of which he himſelf always kept the Keys, his conſtant Cuſtom every Night, under pretence of ſeeing that no Thieves were ſculk'd or ſtoln into any part of his Houſe, was to ſearch every Room in it before he went to Bed; though in reality, the dangerous Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks of Her Cabinet-treaſury, more than his own, were the Thieves and Sculkers he reſolved to ſecure againſt; and though the Engliſh Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom wou'd not permit him to hang a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Italian</hi> Padlock upon it, however he wou'd not be wanting in a true <hi>Italian</hi> Watch and Ward ſet o're it.</p>
               <p>This poor young Thing being kept as his Cage-bird, with only two Pearches in her Aviary, from her Chamber to the Shop, had only the Converſation of the Young and the Gay, the generality of her Husbands Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, with the envious Bar of a Counter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; however ſhe had a great many fond Eyes upon her, for ſhe was poſted at a very fair Stand to wound Hearts <hi>en paſſant,</hi> though ſhe had no convenience of Miniſtring a Cure to them.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48097:12"/>
               <p>Amongſt her thus diſtant Admirers, was a very handſome young Gentleman, who very often bought Goods at the Shop, and would always deal only with the Miſtreſs. This young brisk Fellow that never had an opportunity, beyond a little curſory Rallery, however had made thoſe Amorous Glances, and met thoſe kind encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Returns, that he ſought an occaſion one day of meeting her Maid abroad, and broke his Mind to her in a hundred proteſtation of Paſſion for her Lady. The Girl, who profeſt her ſelf a faithful Confident of her Miſtreſs's, promiſed him all her beſt Aſſiſtance to gain him Acceſs, which having gratefully requited with a Brace of Guineas, and deſired the conveyance of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, He came the next day before Dinner, (as appointed) and buying ſome rich Brocade for a Waſt-coat, this Billet Doux was ſtoln into his Hand.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IF the eaſineſs of the Grant has not cheapned the Value of it, I would tell you your Petition ſhall be anſwered. I confeſs, if the fault were my own, I ſhould colour Scarlet deep at the Frailty I am guilty of; but when dull Sixty Weds gay Twenty, the fault lies at my Husbands door, and 'tis his buſineſs to bluſh, not mine. Come then exactly at Seven this Evening in an ordinary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-gentleman Habit, for Reaſons you ſhall then know, and expect Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48097:13"/>
               <p>The Spark accordingly in a very ſcrubbed Dreſs comes at the Hour, where the Maid was ready to receive him, and guide him up Stairs: He was conducted into a very fair Chamber one pair of Stairs backward, the Room hung with Tapiſtry; the Maid being furniſht with all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, told him in few Words her Maſters Jealouſy: That at preſent he was abroad up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Buſineſs at a neighbouring Coffee-houſe, but in leſs then half an Hour would return; that having a great Cold he was this Night to take a Sweat; for which reaſon his Lady for this Night lay from him in this Chamber; that conſidering the old Gentlemans Cuſtom of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Houſe, ſhe had no place to hide him in, but a great Clock-caſe in the Room that was large enough to hold him, and into which her Maſter would never look; that he muſt wait poſſibly an Hour or two there with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, where ſhe would lock him in, till her Miſtreſs came to Bed.</p>
               <p>The impatient Lover was very willing to undergo ſo ſmall a Pennance, as an Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ſo ſweet a Paradiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and took his Poſt accordingly being ſqueez'd and lock'd into his narrow Wooden Walls.</p>
               <p>The Husband ſoon returning, it was about an Hour and a Half before he prepared for Bed, when entring into this Room, Lord! my Dear (ſays he) our Clock ſtands ſure, or elſe goes near two Hours too ſlow, for the Hand is but juſt turned of Seven, and tis now as much paſt Nine. [For the Reader muſt underſtand that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48097:13"/>the Gentleman's being ſqueez'd into it, had ſtopt the Weights and ſo hindred the Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Clock] However, ſays the old Gentleman, I'll wind it up. The Lady was ſtrangely ſtartled at this, and indeavoured to divert him by ſome little Dalliances. Fye, my Dear, ſays he, be not troubleſome but let me wind up the Clock. No matter for the Clock, anſwered ſhe, have you not a Watch in your Pocket? No, my Dear (anſwered he) it is gone to the Watch-makers to be mended, and I muſt ſet the Clock a going to know how many Hours I muſt Sweat. The Lady was almoſt at her Wits-end, at this Accident, and could no ways ſtop him; when miſſing the Key, the Maid made a blind Excuſe that ſhe had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily lockt it, and carried the Key into the next Room, for which her Maſter heartily Chid her, and bid her fetch it again: The Maid returned, and made anſwer that ſhe had look'd, but could not poſſibly find it; at this the old Gentleman catches hold of the Knot or Button of the Door to pull it open by force: When the Spark within finding he would be certainly diſcovered, preſt forward as the old Man pull'd, and threw the whole Clock-caſe down upon him; at which the Ladies Candle being daſht out, the old Man cried out to the Maid, to run into his Room for her own Candle which ſhe had left there; and in the mean while the Spark ſtole out of the Chamber, where the Maid at the Stair-head handed him down to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48097:14"/>foot of the Stairs almoſt into the Shop, and then run in for her Candle.</p>
               <p>The old Mans crazy Bones, though none of the Strongeſt, yet by good Fortune got no harm by the Fall: 'Tis true he complained that the Clock-caſe fell very heavy, inſomuch that he thought a piece of the Houſe had faln with it, which only gave him a ſlight Bruſh, and did him no great Miſchief. The Lady ſeem'd a little concerned at the Accident, but withal was much pleaſed that he had received no hurt. And the old Man did not ſo much wonder at the fall of it, by Reaſon it was but ſlightly tacked up againſt the Wall, and nailed only into the ſoft Hangings, the Clock it ſelf, which remained unſhaken, being faſtned with Iron work above into the maſſy Wall, and which continued undamaged: So that they ſet it all to rights again, and would it up, and ſo the old Man returned into his own Chamber; where being put to Bed to take his Sweat, and ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Attendance planted about him, the Lady retired into the back Room, whither the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman with his Shoes taken off, was by the kind Damſel convey'd ſoftly up Stairs to Bed to her Miſtreſs; and then ſhe ſhut the Door upon them, and attended her Maſter in the other Room.</p>
               <p>The two Lovers being both gone to Bed, no doubt but they Sympathized with the old Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman; for 'tis ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected that they made Sweating Work too. For warm Love muſt have warm Effects; where we'll
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48097:14"/>leave 'em to all the Delights of Velvet Kiſſes, the beſt and ſofteſt Mercery in the whole Houſe.</p>
               <p>As the Curtains were carefully drawn round them, and all his Cloaths as carefully laid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Bolſter, it was the Maids Poſt to be watchful in the Morning when the Husband roſe (for he was always an early Man) that he ſhould not go in there for fear of waking her Miſtreſs. But there was no danger of that, for the firſt thing he did was to go down into his back Shop, and there in a ſmall Cloſet or Counting-houſe to ſettle his Shop-books. At this Opportunity the young Gallant made haſt to riſe, and was led down by the Maid. The Maſter happening then to be in the Fore-Shop, very haſtily askt her who ſhe had got there? To which the Maid dropping a low Courteſy, made anſwer, only a Corn-cutter, Sir. When came he hither reply'd the old Spark? I brought him in, Sir, anſwered the Wench; when you went firſt into your Counting-houſe, for ſome occaſion I had for him. A Corn-cutter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the old Spark, you are come in good time, Friend; I ſhall uſe you my ſelf: I have a troubleſome Corn on my left foot, and a Toe-nail that grows into the Fleſh.—But take him up again, Huſſey, and give him a Glaſs of our Drink, till I finiſh my Accounts, and come up to him. Ay and thank you noble Maſter, replied the Spark in <hi>Quirpo;</hi> I was Prentice to old <hi>Stephens,</hi> and I thank Heave am as able to ſerve you with a whip and a flaſh at a Foots
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48097:15"/>End, as neatly as any Man in Towne. And ſo the Maid carried him up Stairs.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as he got up again he was under ſome preſent Conſternation how to behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for he fancied himſelf but a damnable awkward Corn-cutter, and as bad provided with Tools for it. However a ſudden thought came into his Head, to carry it off very he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roically, and therefore he deſired the Maid to get him a Penknife, for one of his Corn-cutting Tools. But above all to help him to a piece of Plaſtering, which the Houſe at that time not furniſhing, ſhe preſently be thought her of two large Velvet Temple Patches that ſhe wore for the Head ach; for which, the Gentleman immediately diſmantled a large Snuſh-box of half an ounce of Spaniſh, and clapping in the two Plaiſters, was intirely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with a Salvatory, and indifferently well ſet up for the Manual Management.</p>
               <p>Our young Corn-cutter was no ſooner equipt with his neceſſary Implements, but up came the old Gentleman, and ſitting down in an Elbow-chair, as he pull'd of his Shoe and Stocking, he began to ask him ſome Queſtions. Well Friend (ſays he) what Country-man art thou?—Northweſt Sir, anſwers our Corn-cutter.—Northweſt Friends!—<hi>Corn.</hi> Ay Sir, I was born at <hi>Pancraſs.—Old Gen. Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſs:</hi> From <hi>Cheapſide!</hi> Troth I think that's Northweſt indeed. But Friend, thou ſay'ſt thou wert <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Prentice; does thy Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation take Prentices?—Prentices Sir, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48097:15"/>the Corn-cutter; ay, and all the reaſon in the World. Lord, Sir, we intend to peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the King for a Charter, build a Hall, and ſet up a Corporation of the Right Worſhipful Corn-cutters.—Nay Friend (anſwers the Don) I believe thou art <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Prentice in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; he was juſt ſuch another joking Wag as thou art.—Ay Sir (ſays he) my Maſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me was an ingenious Dog, and I am a true Whelp of his own Breeding.—<hi>Old Gent.</hi> But Friend, are you Maſter of his Art too.— <hi>Corn.</hi> Never fear Sir, my Maſter was too good a Commonwealths-man, to let his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dye with him. And tho' I ſay't as ſhould not ſay't, I ſcorn to turn my Back to the beſt manual Operator in the whole Myſtery.—<hi>Old Gent.</hi> Moſt learnedly ſpoken; then you are ſure you are very dextrous at Corn-cutting.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Dextrous at it! Ay Sir, I'll cut your Corns and pare you Horns, with the beſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Art in <hi>Kent</hi> or <hi>Chriſtendom.—Old Gent.</hi> My Horns? Friend.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Your Nails, Sir, your Nails; Horns and Nails are of the ſame natural homogeneal Growth, as the famous <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> the great Doctor of our Chair, has very learnedly obſerved in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Anatomy.—Why this Fellow (replies the Lady that ſtood by) talks like a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Ay Madam, I have Read <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi>'s Problems. If your Ladyſhip never ſaw it, I'll lend it you.—<hi>Lady.</hi> Nay, troth, this is a merry Fellow indeed.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Merry Madam, why 'tis the beſt Tool of my Trade;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48097:16"/>my Maſter got half his Eſtate by it.—Eſtate! reply'd the Mercer; I thoguht he had dy'd in <hi>Sutton</hi>'s Hoſpital.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Ay Sir, no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that, he had good Lands and Livings to my Knowledge.—<hi>Old Gent.</hi> Lands and Livings, prethee in what part of the World?—<hi>Corn.</hi> Why in Gypſey Land. We Corn-cutters are mungril Gypſies.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Our Lands and our Livings,</l>
                  <l>Are of other Folks givings;</l>
                  <l>And ſo rubs the World away.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lady.</hi> Troth my Dear, I like this Fellow well, I care not if I come under his Hands.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Truly Madam, I ſhall uſe you very gently, for I have a very neat Hand at Womens Work.—<hi>Lady.</hi> Now I think on't I have a kind of a ſoft Corn on the inſide of one of my great Toes that dos ſo pain me.—<hi>Corn.</hi> A Pain between your two great Toes! You are not the firſt fair Lady that has been troubled with that Malady. But Madam, if I don't preſently eaſe you.—<hi>Lady.</hi> Sayſt thou ſo; then call ſome Morning towards the end of the Week, and I'll take a Caſt of your Office.</p>
               <p>By this time, the old Gentleman was ready for the manual Operation, and had ſhew'd where his Grievance lay. Well Sir, ſays the Corn-cutter, ſhall I go through ſtitch with you, and take out your Corn, Root and Branch; or ſhall I leave ſome few ſtrings of it behind me, to have your Cuſtom another time? Nay Friend,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48097:16"/>replies the Don, if you have an Art to take it off Root and Branch that it will never grow again; pray uſe your beſt Skill, though I pay you double Fees for't.—<hi>Corn.</hi> Why then I'll tell you; I have a Plaiſter here in my Box, that will ſo ripen it in one 24 Hours, that by to morrow Morning when I ſhall come again, I'll make ſuch clever Work on't, that I'll lay my Life to a half penny worth of Butter-milk, you ſhall never hear more on't.—<hi>Old Gent.</hi> Sayſt thou ſo! Then prithee lay on thy Plaiſter. But what, a Velvet Plaiſter?—<hi>Corn.</hi> Ay Sir, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuit my Surgery to my Cuſtomers. Your Worſhip has paſt your Braſs Chain, and your pluſh Jerkin, and your rich Batchelorſhip, and may live to be an Alderman: And ſo a Velvet patch to a Velvet jump, is all <hi>ſecundum artem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having reſerved the Corn-Cure for the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the old Gentleman however deſired the other part of his Office, <hi>viz.</hi> The paring of his Nails; but our Corn-cutter (to ſhorten the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) excuſed that too, till to morrow Morning, for want of an extraordinary Tool that he ſaid, he had at the Grinders, which he would bring with him, and which ſhou'd do it much more eaſily than any of his preſent Implements he had about him. And ſo the old Spark ſtealing a Shilling into his hand, the young Artiſt went off with flying Colours.</p>
               <p>The next Morning our young Spark, ſent a more able Operator, whom he rewarded with a brace of Crowns to go in his ſtead, and make an excuſe for him, that he was faln Ill, and was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48097:17"/>afraid of the new Fever, and for that Reaſon, had ſent his Deputy.</p>
               <p>One Evening at the end of the Week, the Ladies Maid came to his Lodging from her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, to tell him, That the morrow Morning following, the Coaſt would be clear, for her Husband was to be out the whole Forenoon: And therefore ſhe deſired his Company, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring him withal, to bring his Tools along with him. Ay Chicken, reply'd the Spark, I never go to a fair Lady without 'em. Nay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Girl, I mean your Corn-cutting Tools, for you muſt come in that Habit again. So the Gentleman repaying her former Favours, he preſented the Girl with ten Guineas, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be punctual at the Aſſignation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Morning he made his Viſit at Eight, when the Lady in a looſe Dreſs, a Diſhabilee, only her morning Gown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in her own Chamber was ready to receive him: And here he continued till near Noon, for the Lady had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry private and important Affairs with him; for her Fondneſs would not yield to part with him, till the laſt Minute when ſhe was forced to loſe him; nor was he Idle all the while, for no doubt ſhe found Work enough for ſo dear an Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator.</p>
               <p>Between Eleven and Twelve the Husband returned, and the Corn-cutter was diſmis'd, the Maid attending him down to the Shop door. It happened that the Husband had brought home with him a very eminent Citizen, a Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet,</hi> who ſeeing a Face paſs by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48097:17"/>him that he was ſo very well acquainted with, catch'd hold of our young Spark; why how now, crys the Caſh-broker? What have we got here, my good old Friend Sir <hi>William</hi> in Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade? Sir <hi>William,</hi> Sir! anſwer'd the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, ſomewhat ſurpriz'd; why Sir, do you know this Man? Know him, Sir! reply'd the Banker; ay Sir, I think I have Reaſon to know him, for I have Six Thouſand Pounds of his in my Hands. Lord have Mercy upon us, (crys the old Man, lifting up his Eyes to Heaven, and turning as pale as Death,) a Sir <hi>William!</hi> and Six Thouſand Pound, and my Wives Corn-cutter, Oh! I a Sir <hi>William!</hi> (anſwer'd the young Spark) and Six Thouſand Pound; faith Maſter woul'd you would make your words true; I gad, if I had but half that Mony, I'd build one of the Steeple's of <hi>Pauls.</hi> I beg your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don honeſt Fellow, reply'd the Goldſmith, (finding he had done Miſchief, and ſmelling a Trick,) now I hear thee ſpeak, I find my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; thou haſt a Face as like a <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, as one Apple's like another; but thy Voice is no more like his, than a Bagpipe to a Recorder. And ſo the young Spark ſcrap'd him a Leg, and march'd off.</p>
               <p>Lord Sir, continu'd the Banker, how two Faces may be alike. I remember I read a Story of a Shooe-maker of <hi>Maidſtone</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in <hi>Harry</hi> the Eighths Reign, that was ſo like the King, that he was ſent for up to Court; and in one of the King's Veſts, paſt through the whole Court at <hi>Whitehall</hi> ſaluted for the King, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48097:18"/>undiſcovered by all his Guards; and coming to the King's Preſence, the King ſaw his own Picture ſo exactly, that he ask'd the fellow Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſely, If his Mother had never been at Court? No, reply'd the noble Cordwainer, <hi>but my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has been there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King was ſo very well pleaſed with ſo ſmart and ingenious a Repartee, that he ſetled a very fair Eſtate upon his Royal Repreſentative, and made him that little Prince of a <hi>Criſpin,</hi> a Degree above his Awle or his paring Knife.</p>
               <p>The good old Gentleman was mightily pleaſed with this Story, thanked the kind Banker for the Relation, laugh'd at his own groundleſs ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, making all the due Application of the Story to his own Caſe; and went off with all the intire Satisfaction and Peace, like a true City Husband, with full Faith and Confidence in his innocent Yoke-mate, and her honeſt Corn-cutter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48097:18"/>
               <head>INTRIEGUE III.</head>
               <p>ABOVE a year before the Revolution, a young Gentleman, whom wee'll call <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine,</hi> of very Honourable Birth and Education, the ſecond Brother to an eminent Baronet in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> fell paſſionately in Love with a young Country Gentlewoman, the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of a Father, who (bating his over-much Inclination to Avarice, even to a Fault,) was a very accompliſh'd Man, and the Maſter of many eminent Virtues. It unhappily fell out, (if we may venture to Arraign the diſtribution of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence) that this young Lover, though with the too ſlender Fortune of a younger Brother, was a Perſon of that Gallantry, Wit, Spirit and Courage, ſo much beyond the weaker Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the more cloudy Intellects of his elder Brother, that ſwept the whole Eſtate from him; that 'tis much to be pitied that no other Title, but the ſtart of a year into the world before him, ſhould load this Saturnine elder Birth with above Two Thouſand <hi>per Annum,</hi> and the Sprightlier younger Brother ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little more than as many Hundreds.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48097:19"/>
               <p>This young Lover with the foremention'd Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, made a very fortunate Attack upon the young Ladies Heart, with a ſucceſs, even to his own utmoſt Wiſhes; and when the mutual Faith was plighted, and not till then, (there remaining nothing now but Obedience to be conſulted) the Fathers conſent was ask'd to the Marriage, being now told that he had long lov'd his Daughter, the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> (for that ſhall be her Name) and there was nothing wanting but his paternal Aſſent and Bleſſing to Crown their mutual Felicity. The Father ſeem'd much ſurpriz'd at this Narration, and fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a very great Paſſion at the Boldneſs of his Daughter, to receive and encourage a Suiter, without giving him an earlier Account of the Matter; urging, that it was the higheſt Breach of her filial Duty to keep any thing of this kind conceal'd from a Parent, it being his equal Right to have a concurrence, as well in the diſpoſal of her Heart, (nay, even her very Looks) as of her Perſon. In ſhort, here was the paternal Authority infringed, and nothing could pacify the angry Father.</p>
               <p>But all this Out-cry (which indeed was but the pretence) was really Founded upon a more heinous Diſguſt: Neither the Quality nor Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the young Lover were any ways Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor the private Commerce of Love ſo long manag'd betwixt the young couple was the true capital Crime: No, her Father was able to give her half Five Thouſand Pound Portion, and the poor young Gentlemans worldly Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48097:19"/>did not deſerve ſuch a Fortune. If the elder Brother, 'tis true, had been her humble Servant, the infringement of the paternal Power had then been a more venial Sin: A Baronet, and Two Thouſand a year, might have woo'd, won, nay, and worn her too, without half this Quarrel.</p>
               <p>To ſhorten this part of my Hiſtory, 'tis enough to tell you, that the Father is wholly Inexorable, and the Daughter being all Duty, dares not Rebel, though to be the happieſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the World, as ſuch the Embraces of her dear <hi>Peregrine</hi> had undoubtedly made her: Inſomuch, that her Fathers conſent being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unconquerable, there's nothing but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair and Miſery before their Eyes; for poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly never was Love ſo Paſſionate, as between the languiſhing <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and the mourning <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> Mourning indeed, for that melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Epithite was intirely her own, under her infinite Griefs at her hard Fathers Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>The defeated Lovers, under all the Agonies imaginable, nevertheleſs renew'd their eternal Engagement of Fidelity; the Lady on her part made a ſolemn Vow, that ſhe would never Marry any Man whilſt her <hi>Peregrine</hi> liv'd; and he, with as many hearty Oaths bound himſelf under the ſame Obligation. All their Hopes, if any, were, that poſſibly her Father, or his Brother might die, and by that means, either the Command of her Fortunes in her own hands would render her Miſtreſs of her ſelf; or the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48097:20"/>advance of his would mollify an obdurate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who in ſpight of all his other Pretenſions, ſhe was very well ſatisfied had no true Obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to bar their Happineſs, but the ſlender Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony of her dear <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this inviolable Contract between 'em, the poor Gentleman in tenderneſs to the Peace of his darling Miſtreſs, (being ſenſible if he ſtay'd in <hi>England,</hi> he ſhould be eternally hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about her, even poſſibly to the ruin of her very Freedom, under the Jealouſie of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Father, or ſome other paternal Frowns that his Preſence might pull down upon her) reſolved to take the opportunity of Travelling Abroad with a young <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobleman, his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and intimate Friend.</p>
               <p>In his Abſence according to mutual Promiſes, a Correſpondence was held between 'em by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the moſt Tender and Paſſionate that all the Inſpirations of Love could dictate; which for the ſafer conveyance to her hand, was agreed between them, they ſhould be all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to her Maid (her particular Confident) who conſtantly attended the Poſt-houſe in the Town for their Receipt, to prevent any Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. The Father after his Departure, who was no Stranger to his Abſence, nor that Coaſt of the World where-ever he rambled, (for his Suſpicion made him ſet up for a Spy, and keep Intelligence on that very Account) took an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion one day to preſent his Daughter with a very rich Scrutore, to which he had provided a double Set of Keys. This noble Preſent, was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48097:20"/>ſoon made the young Ladies Cloſet-favourite, the Cabinet where the greateſt Treaſure of her Life, her <hi>Peregrines</hi> Letters were repoſited; to which the Father, at favourable opportunities, by the help of his falſe Keys, had all the Acceſs he deſired; and there was not that Secret of their Souls, at leaſt, that they truſted to Black and White, that he was a Stranger to: For he read both <hi>Peregrines</hi> and his Daughters Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the innocent Lady keeping the Copies of her own, as well as the Originals of her dear <hi>Peregrines,</hi> under the ſame Lock and Key.</p>
               <p>The Father now plainly perceived the Vows and Contracts made between 'em, which he likewiſe ſound inviolable; not only by their mutual Proteſtations, but likewiſe by daily Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: For in leſs than half a Years time, the Fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Beauty (for ſhe had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stock of Charms) had attracted her more than half a Score new Idolaters, ſome of them of the higheſt Eſtates and Quality, but all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and ſlighted: Nay, the very Commands of a Father, all rejected, ſhe being utterly Deaf to all Arguments, Reaſon, or any Authority whatever, on that Subject.</p>
               <p>This Diſcovery gave the Father a great deal of diſquiet, who ſaw his whole Ambition fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, in all his endeavours for the happy Diſpoſal of his Daughter; nevertheleſs, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal all Suſpicions from his Daughter of any Diſcovery whatever, in all his reſentments againſt her continued Deafneſs and Obſtinacy, he took care not to let drop a Word that ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48097:21"/>intimate his leaſt knowledge of her Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with <hi>Peregrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time it hapned that the Father took a particular Fancy to leave his Country Reſidence, and take a great Houſe in <hi>Linclon</hi>'s-Inn Fields; whither the greateſt part of his Goods and Furniture was removed, and his whole Family tranſplanted to <hi>London.</hi> The young Lady who gave her Lover Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her removal, continued her foreign Correſpondence with her <hi>Pregrine.</hi> About the time of her arrival at <hi>London,</hi> her <hi>Peregrine</hi> had then Travell'd through all <hi>france,</hi> viſited ſeveral Courts in <hi>Italy,</hi> and was ſettled for the whole Winter Seaſon at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> carried her Charms to <hi>London,</hi> ſo ſhe made her new Conqueſts there. And amongſt a Crowd of Gazers upon ſo ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated a Beauty, it happen'd that a very rich Merchant, dignified with a Knighthood, was made one of her Captives. 'Tis true, he was a Widower, had ſeveral Children, and was aged about Fifty, almoſt old enough for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Grand father; but ſtill he had a vaſt Eſtate, was a Man of no mean parts; and to manage his Addreſſes to ſo young a Lady, with the true arts of Policy, he made his ſtrongeſt Attack upon the Father; and to bribe him to his Party, nay, and poſſibly endear the young Lady too, by ſo generous an Offer, he propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſettle her a Jointure more than doubly anſwerable to her Fortunes, and yet receive not one Penny of Portion with her; giving
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48097:21"/>her Father free leave to diſpoſe of that to the bettering his younger Childrens Portions. This wonderful Generoſity carried a high ſway with the Father; and though God knows but little influence upon the Daughter, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever her acknowledgment of ſo frank a Lover, kept her in the bounds of ſomewhat more than ordinary Civility towards him. Beſides, though in all her Coldneſs to all the tenders of Love from any thing but her dear <hi>Peregrine,</hi> both her Prudence and good Breeding always gave a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courteous Reception to all her Adorers, how coldly ſoever ſhe received the Adoration: And even her very Refuſals, nay her coyeſt Diſdain, had a peculiar Grace and Air in it, that ſpoke her the Miſtreſs of an admirable Wit and Addreſs.</p>
               <p>Her Father, who now grew almoſt enamour'd of his rich and generous Merchant-pretender, nevertheleſs daily found both by his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's and <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s Letters (for he kept the old Cuſtom of prying into her Cabinet) that neither Time, Diſtance, nor Abſence, could ſhake her Engagements with <hi>Peregrine;</hi> and conſequently whilſt that inviolable League held firm, all other Hopes or Attempts were wholly Fruitleſs: And therefore began to think of ſome Plots or Stratagems, if poſſible, to cut this fatal Gordian.</p>
               <p>Accordingly, as Miſcheif never wants a Prompter, he ſoon furniſht himſelf with edge Tools for that illnatur'd Work: For firſt he went to the grand Poſt-office, and there cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48097:22"/>one of the Poſt-officers to ſtop all Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Letters directed to ſuch a young Woman ſo named—<hi>viz.</hi> His Daughters Confident, which by Virtue of a Golden Bribe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily granted him; and for a Fortnights time together, all <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s Letters which innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continued that Superſcription, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd at the Poſt office, and received by the Father: After this, he feigned a very long Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (which received the Poſt-mark) as from the young Nobleman, dated from his very Lodgings near the <hi>Vatican</hi> (from whence <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi> had always dated before, and which much contributed to the Credit of the Contents) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Young Lady her ſelf, preparing her firſt with a great many artful and tender Expreſſions, for the Reception of the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Relation he was going to make. In fine the long doleful Epiſtle concluded with the deplorable Account of the Death of her dear <hi>Peregrine,</hi> who dyed of an Apoplexy; and that having had the Honour of his particular Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Confidence, he made bold to be this ungrateful Meſſenger, whilſt mixing his own Tears for ſo dear a Friend, with thoſe from her own fair Eyes for ſo faithful a Lover, who as he lived, died only Hers; he promiſed her to take care of all her Letters, which as ſo many Reliques, he had Sealed up, together with ſome ſmull Jewels and Rarities deſign'd by the kind <hi>Peregrine,</hi> for a Preſent to his ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> and which being not ſo portable by the publick Poſt, ſhould with all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48097:22"/>Speed be convey'd to her fair Hands by ſome properer way.</p>
               <p>I need not tell my Reader how fatally this Paper Thunder-bolt ſtruck the poor afflicted <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> who, ſweet Innocence, not in the leaſt ſuſpecting the Forgery, ſunk under that Load of Grief, that was almoſt inexpreſſible. Her Father, inquiring the Fountain-head of all theſe ſudden floods of Tears, ſhe very frankly ſhewed him the fatal Letter, as having now no farther occaſion of Privacy or Reſerves, confeſſing her whole Correſpondence and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements (as much as her Sighs would give her utterance) with her dear <hi>Peregrine.</hi> The Father very cunningly, not in the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting her Diſobedience in ſuch a Confeſſion, joyn'd with her in her very Tears, and expreſt himſelf little leſs a Mourner than her, aſſuring her that his Pity for his unfortunate Death, had made a very great Converſion upon him, and much ſoften'd a great many hard Thoughts which he had formerly very unkindly conceived againſt him.</p>
               <p>During her daily repeated Sighs for her truly lamented <hi>Peregrine,</hi> her Father was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Condoler with her, till at laſt, telling her how 'twas impoſſible to combat the Decrees of heaven, he beſought her to bury her Griefs in her <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s Grave; and as her Vows of Fidelity were now cancell'd in his Death, to think of ſome leſs melancholy Subject; and if ſhe tendered either her own Felicity, or her Fathers Satisfaction, ſhe would condeſcend to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48097:23"/>lend a kind Ear to her kneeling City Knight, and Reign both the Miſtreſs of ſo faithful a Heart, and ſo ample a Fortune.</p>
               <p>The fair Mourner you may well believe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived but very little Harmony from ſo ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Tune as Love; however, taking her Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which ſhe every Night water'd with a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaned melting Tears; amongſt the Reflections of her preſent Miſery, ſhe began to conſider of the diſpoſal of her future mourning Hours of Life, under the Loſs of her never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten dear <hi>Peregrine.</hi> She well knew there would be no long Reſiſtance againſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Father: For how little ſoever the Taſt of Love would reliſh with her, ſhe muſt at laſt be forced to ſit down with that unpala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Feaſt called Matrimony. And truly, if ſhe muſt have a Husband, ſhe reflected that the beſt Choice ſhe could ever make would be her City Merchant. For as all Fondneſs or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light died with her <hi>Peregrine,</hi> ſhe thought that her cold Embraces could now be no where bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſtowed, than upon reverend Five and fifty, <hi>viz.</hi> her Widower Knight, her Ice and his Age being the moſt ſuitable Match. For to Marry any Gentleman of Birth, Youth and Honour, ſhe thought would be a kind of Cheat and Deluſion (which her Candor and Integrity utterly abhorred) by lodging ſo heartleſs a lump of Wedlock in the Boſom of Deſert and Worth, that both required and merited a more cheerful Mate than ſuch a drooping Turtle ſhould ever make. Beſides, what was yet the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48097:23"/>ſtrongeſt Obligation; ſhe ſtood ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to the Love and Memory of her dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and only dear <hi>Peregrine,</hi> that ſhe fancied it an open Violation of her very Vows to that only Lord of all her plighted Faith (a Bond that even Death could never Break) to Sleep in any young and charming Lovers Arms; being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to pay that Pious Duty to his very Name, as never to taſt the true Joys of Life, which nothing but <hi>Peregrine</hi> could, or at leaſt no Man elſe ſhall ever give her. And therefore if ſhe Marries, it ſhall be to her antiquated humble City Servant, whoſe Perſon and Age being both ſo very little agreeable, ſhe thought it ſo far from a Blemiſh or Reproach to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, or any Invaſion of her <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s ever ſacred Right, that on the contrary ſhe rather eſteem'd it as no other than giving up her ſelf a perfect Sacrifice, even to her dear <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi>'s ever darling Memory, by tying her Youth and Beauty, to ſo taſtleſs a Wedlock Bed, a Pennance more than Pleaſure; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a kind of voluntary Oblation even of her whole Peace of Life (under ſo mortifying a ſhackle) to the very Aſhes and Name of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This generous, though a little Romantick Reſolution, being ſpurred on by her Fathers daily Importunities, ſo prevail'd at laſt, that in leſs than a Month ſhe Married her Knight; where we'll leave her in her Wedding ſheets, in all the Embraces, though not all the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports of Wedlock; and make a ſhort Viſit to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48097:24"/>her poor Traveller at <hi>Rome.</hi>—Above a Month (an Age in a Lovers Calendar) had now paſt, ſince he received one Line from his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania:</hi> An Hundred melancholy Reflections he made upon ſo ſtrange a Silence: Sometimes he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied ſhe might be Indiſpoſed; but then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered her Maid would have written for her: Her Silence he durſt not impute to any Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or Infidelity, for he had too good an Opinion of ſuch inviolable Truth. Poſſibly then her Father had diſcover'd their Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or intercepted his Letters; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſent a Letter to her, incloſed in another to a Merchant his Friend, in <hi>London;</hi> with a particular Charge of a private Delivery.</p>
               <p>He need not have given him ſo ſtrict a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in that Point. For coming to deliver a Letter from a young Spark to a Married La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, (as ſuch indeed he found her) he thought it high Prudence to uſe the beſt Caution and Privacy in ſuch an Errand. Accordingly he took the opportunity of meeting her Abroad one Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with no Company but that of her Maid, as ſhe was going to Church to Prayers. He no ſooner gave her the Letter, and ſhe ſaw but the Superſcription, but well remembering the Hand, ſhe turned as Pale as Death, and looking almoſt Frightfully in the Meſſengers Face, ſhe askt, <hi>From whence comes this?</hi> From Mr. <hi>Peregrine</hi>—replyed the Merchant, Sir <hi>Peregrine, I ſhould ſay: For his Brother's newly Dead, and we hope we ſnall ſee him in</hi> England, <hi>to take poſſeſſion of</hi>—Before he could finiſh his ſhort Speech, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48097:24"/>fell down Dead in a Swoon into her Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Arms, letting drop the Letter from her Hand: The poor Maid very much concern'd at her Ladies Indiſpoſition, and more at the fatal cauſe of it; immediately call'd a Coach, into which, with ſome help, ſhe got her poor Miſtreſs; and having ſecured the Letter, ſhe bid the Coach-man drive ſoftly to the next Fields, as prudently thinking it the beſt Policy, not to drive home immediately, but firſt a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to recompoſe her ſad Ladies ſurprizing Afflictions, and recover her loſt Senſes; ſo much the more cautiouſly to manage this fatal Accident, to the prevention of raiſing any jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ill Blood at home: For the Knight was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly a Stranger to the whole Hiſtory of this darling Rival.</p>
               <p>As the Coach drove through <hi>Moor-feilds</hi> (for they ſet out from the <hi>Change</hi>) the Lady by the Care of her Maid, was brought a little to her Senſes again: And the Coach-man being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to drive very ſlowly, ſhe turned her drowned Eyes to the Reading of her <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi>'s Letter, the Subject poſſibly the tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that the moſt tranſported Paſſion cou'd write. He began firſt in a few mourning Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle murmurs to tell her, That above a whole Month had paſt in which he had not received one Line from his Divine <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania:</hi> But that he cou'd impute only to ſome unhappy Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, not to any Coldneſs or Forgetfulneſs, for his Soul was too full of the darling Virtues of his dear <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> to apprehend even but a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48097:25"/>ſhadow of a Change, in ſuch unſhaken Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Faith, Honour, Love, and every Charm of Heaven, all joyn'd in his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to reward his long, long Sighs and Tears, he told her he had newly received a Letter with an Account of his Brothers Death, by which the whole Eſtate and Honour of his Family devolv'd upon him, and that he was immediately following his Letter, which was only ſent with the Olave-branch before him: That he was poſting with all the Wings of Love to the Arms of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> for now he doubted not but he ſhould be able to melt down her obdurate Father into Juſtice and Mercy. In ſhort, he run on with ſo many hundred Tranſports and Extaſies upon the proſpect of his approaching Felicity, in the Embraces of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> as if he had ſeen no leſs than the Clouds opening, and the Angels deſcending, and all the whole Joys of Heaven pouring down upon his Head.</p>
               <p>Oh do but think, what an Epiſtle was here written, and what Eyes were here to read it! 'Tis true, ſhe read it out, and I dare not ſay either with a more than Womans ſtrength or courage ſhe out-liv'd the reading it. For though the poor <hi>Fidelia,</hi> her Maid, made a hard ſhift to prevent her relapſe into her former ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fit; however 'twas only to ſuffer the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a more lingering Death. For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſo killing as this Language from her dear <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and nothing ſo miferable as the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48097:25"/>wretched and hardfated <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> that lives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the reading it. It is impoſſible to expreſs the Flood, the Torrent, nay, the Deluge of Tears, that followed this fatal Diſcovery of the inevitable Miſeries, Deſpair and Ruin, that now lay before her.</p>
               <p>But not to hold my Reader too long in this melancholy Relation, <hi>Fidelia</hi> at length prevail'd that they ſhould drive home, and 'twas agreed between 'em, that whatever indiſpoſition at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended her unhappy Miſtreſs, (for this ſhock was enough to ſtagger a ſtronger Heart) that the Cauſe of her Affliction ſhould be concealed with all the Caution and Care imaginable. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhe returned home, where ſhe gave her ſelf up to all the moſt violent Tranſports of Grief that a breaking Heart could utter. The poor Knight at home was infinitely ſurpriz'd at the red Eyes of his dear Lady; but <hi>Fidelia</hi> had a nimble excuſe to ſalve all, by telling him that 'twas an Indiſpoſition of her Miſtreſs's, that had attended her from her very Youth. The good Man immediately poſted away a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for a Phyſitian; but <hi>Fidelia</hi> ſtop'd him, deſiring (and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> join'd in her requeſt) that no Doctor might be ſent for, but <hi>Fidelias</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (at that time a young Practitioner in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, living not far off.) The kind Husband who was all Obedience to the Commands of his dear young Lady, could not deny her any thing; and therefore the young <hi>Eſculapius</hi> being ſent for, <hi>Fidelia</hi> very cunningly managed the Matter, that the Doctor gave in his Report
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48097:26"/>of his Ladies Diſtemper, as the Maids, not the Miſtreſs's Pulſe beat; nay, the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes of her Cure, were all of her own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: For the young Doctor very readily (as tutor'd by his Siſter) declared that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of her Diſeaſe, required Silence and Reſt; that it was abſolutely neceſſary ſhe ſhould lie alone, till her Recovery. The poor Man, tho' with much Regret, ſubmitted to the Sentence of being excluded from his dear Spouſe's Arms for ſome few widow'd Nights: However im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a Confidence in her young Doctor's Skill and Judgment, he prayed for his ſucceſs in the reſtoration of her Health; and ſo reſign'd her to the care of Heaven, and into the hands of Art.</p>
               <p>This Project was very uſeful in the poor Lady's Circumſtances; for lying alone, with <hi>Fidelia</hi> in a Pallate-Bed by her, 'twas not only ſome eaſe to her Sorrows that ſhe could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely give her ſelf up to her Sighs for her <hi>Peregrine;</hi> but likewiſe ſhe had rid her ſelf of the ungrateful Embraces of a Tyrant and an Uſurper, for as ſuch ſhe look'd upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſſeſſor of her Bed, as only mounted thither by Cheats, Plots, Forgery, Treaſon and Deluſion. In all her apprehenſions of Shame and Confuſion at the return of her <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrine,</hi> (for ſee him ſhe is reſolv'd, though ſhe die at his Feet) ſhe has this only dawn of hopes of one kind beam of Pity and Pardon from him; when in all the Miſeries her bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Father has heap'd upon her, her very
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48097:26"/>Choice of a Husband, and the Reaſons of that choice, ſhould convince him, that ſhe had Truth even in her Falſhood. For ſince an irreſiſtible Power, had compell'd her into the Bonds of Matrimony, ſhe had choſen a Shackle, not a Bracelet, by a Match of that inequality of Age to her Youth and Charms, as might ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently teſtifie that, 'tis true, the Right even of her dead <hi>Peregrine</hi> might be ſupplanted by Conſtraint and Force, but never alienated by Delight, Deſire and Inclination.</p>
               <p>The Father, as you may imagine, was ſtrangely mortify'd at the News of his Daughter's Ilneſs, but more at the unhappy cauſe of it; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt trembles to approach the fair Ruins he was now ſenſible himſelf had only made. 'Tis true, the poor Lady received him with all the filial Duty and Reſpect, far beyond the common For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſuch Unpardonable Injuries: 'Tis true, ſhe Charged her whole Deſtruction, and ſhe much fears her Death, upon his unnatural Cruelty; however, ſhe freely forgives him; and would make it even her laſt dying Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or at leaſt her dying Prayer (for her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſhe feared had now no Power) to her wrong'd <hi>Peregrine,</hi> to ſeal him that ſame Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and to bury all Reſentments againſt the unkind Father, in the unhappy Daughters Grave.</p>
               <p>This infinite Goodneſs of the ſweet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> ſtruck him ſo near the Heart, if poſſible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſhock of her very Sufferings and his own Injuſtice; inſomuch, that there never
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48097:27"/>was a more hearty Mourner, and a truer Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, than her unfortunate Father.—But to leave him to his Sorrows, and to bring over our young Traveller, rap'd up even in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice it ſelf, with thoſe Dreams, thoſe Hopes and all thoſe dazling Viſions, of almoſt more than mortal Happineſs in his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Arms: Think what a <hi>Phaeton</hi>'s Fall muſt here be; when little leſs than daſh'd down from Heaven, his very firſt Salute on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Shore, (if Ravens Croaks, and Mandrakes Groans can be Salutations) is the whole Story of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Marriage. For ſuch prudent care was taken both by the lady and the Father, that Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance lay ready at his Tranſport from <hi>Callais</hi> to <hi>Dover,</hi> (for in pure Expedition, he croſt the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and came Poſt by Land, arriving in <hi>England</hi> in five days after his Letter) on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to prepare him for the whole mournful Narrative, thereby to prevent thoſe too vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and poſſibly thoſe too fatal Tranſports of Fury, that otherwiſe, upon any other Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the ungrateful News, might have broken out. Beſides, it was both high Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Juſtice, to have the whole Tale de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in all its true Circumſtances; as well for the Vindication of the poor Ladies Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as for ſome little alleviation of the poor Gentlemans Peace, when the whole Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Scene of his loſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> ſet forth in its true Light, would appear to have more the Hand of Fate in it, than Infidelity.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48097:27"/>
               <p>Beſides, this preparation (the whole Story being faithfully related, and as generouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved) in ſome meaſure a little paved the way for the interveiw of the two unfortunate Lovers, which the next morning after his arrival in <hi>London,</hi> by the management of <hi>Fidelia,</hi> was made between 'em. When <hi>Peregrine</hi> meeting the ſtill charming Eyes of his ever adored <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> (for though Sickneſs and Sorrow had emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied half their Quiver, yet ſtill they had Darts enough to kill) inſtead of Revilings, Upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or Reproaches at any thing of Levity, Forgetfulneſs or Inconſtancy, in the too haſty Marriage of his loſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania:</hi> On the contrary, here was nothing but wet Eyes, bent Knees, a proſtrate Lover thrown dying at her Feet, and the languiſhing and breathleſs <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> at the ſame time falling dead into his Arms; that 'twas almoſt a Queſtion in all the Agonies of Grief on one ſide, and Tenderneſs on the other, which held faſteſt, the Embraces of Love, or thoſe of Death between 'em.</p>
               <p>When they had both recovered Life enough for Breath, and Breath enough for Words, and recollected Senſe enough to find a Tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em; what Torrent of Murmurs were here pour'd forth, and all againſt their cruel Stars, but a more cruel Father; the over-ruling Powers that had fated their Deſtruction! For their whole Miſery lies at no other Door: The generous <hi>Peregrine</hi> has no complaint at any thing but Deſtiny: The Eyes of Love can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Faith and Virtue, in that ſweet delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48097:28"/>Innocence his dear <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> and even Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf may be Faulty, when ſhe cannot.</p>
               <p>'Twas in this kind of Entertainment, that the Conference laſted a whole Afternoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, when they only Adjourned till to morrow after Dinner, to renew the ſame Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs, and all the ſame Raptures over again. For here is only the beginning, to what muſt never have an end: For the complaints of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Lovers are Number leſs.</p>
               <p>The good-natured Knight at home, had na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally a great ſtock of Faith, and therefore was not over-jealous of the innocent Liberties his young Lady took. Beſides, her Doctor in Ordinary, had given in his Judgment, That Diverſion and walking Abroad, would be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtrumental in the reſtoration of her Health; which gave her all the unqueſtion'd Freedom of going Abroad, and meeting her <hi>Peregrine</hi> as often as ſhe pleaſed. Theſe meetings were very often repeated, and were wholly made up of nothing but Love. <hi>Peregrine</hi> amongſt a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred other Proteſtations, made a ſolemn Vow which he bound with all the moſt vehement Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, that he would live and die hers and only hers; that he would tire out the whole Malice of his Stars, and wait the very Death of her Husband, for the poſſeſſion of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> for he made an abſolute Abjuration to all the Sex beſide. This Proteſtation, and indeed a hundred more, were all graciouſly received by the kind <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> who wanted no returns of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination and Love, to ſo devoted an Adorer.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:48097:28"/>
               <p>And though with all the imaginable endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments between 'em, theſe private Viſits were almoſt daily renew'd; however the unſatisfied <hi>Peregrine,</hi> began to repine at the Felicities of his envied Rival; and though they never met but they melted into all the Tenderneſs of twining Embraces, and their Souls met a hundred times over, not only at their languiſhing Eyes, but even at their burning Lips, a liberty the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Peregrine</hi> dayly more and more encroach'd upon the languiſhing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> however not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with all theſe Favours, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear openly murmuring, even at thoſe yet more charming Bliſſes ſhe beſtow'd on his happier Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, who in all his pretended lawful Poſſeſſion, had not half the juſt and equitable Right of <hi>Peregrine. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> reprimanded him for ſo unkind a Reproach, aſſuring him, that if he knew how thoſe Bliſſes, as he was pleas'd to call them, were extorted from her, even with the whole coldneſs of a <hi>Lucretia,</hi> he would be far from envying the poor Poſſeſſor, that little deſpicable Thief, that only rifled an empty Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet; his very Embraces being the perfect Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Slavery, all Violence and Arbitrary Power on one ſide, and nothing but Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Paſſive Obedience on the other. No, <hi>Peregrine,</hi> continued ſhe, never envy the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer at ſo cold an Altar of Love, where he may bring Fires, but never find any. This De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration was ſo very kind, that he threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at her Feet, to thank the fair obliging good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the ſweet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> would by no
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48097:29"/>means ſuffer, but gently raiſing him up with her fair hand, ſhe told him; That Poſture and theſe Acknowledgments were more than he ow'd her; for there are no Thanks due for Duty. If ſhe was all this coldneſs to that Poſſeſſor he ſo unjuſtly envy'd, it was but a juſt Debt ſhe paid, even to the dead, and much more to the living <hi>Peregrine.</hi>—This ſecond Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion rapt him into new Tranſports; and now inſtead of his bending Knees at her Feet, he threw his graſping Arms about her Neck, and pour'd his melting Soul into thoſe charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lips that delivered ſuch raviſhing Oracles.</p>
               <p>As the daily Converſation continued, and a hundred more and more paſſionate Vows and Endearments paſt between 'em, the amorous unſatisfied <hi>Peregrine</hi> could not forbear telling her; That there were yet infinitely diviner Bleſſings in her Power, and which, if ſhe would give him leave to remonſtrate his Sufferings, he had ſome Plea even to ask of her. (For tho' he found a riſing Crimſon in the Cheeks of his Bluſhing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> however, he conjured her to give him the Favour of hearing him out:) He deſired her therefore, continuing the Subject, to call to remembrance their firſt mutual Vows of Fidelity made between 'em, that had ſworn and ſealed their plighted Souls; what new Vows he had ſince made of all Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations to the whole Sexe's Charms but his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi> How that if there was a fatal Marriage knot that ſeem'd to bar his Joys; however, what Villany, Treaſon and Injuſtice,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48097:29"/>tied that Knot; and how venial muſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion even of her higheſt Favours be, under ſo honeſt and juſt a Repriſal, from ſo much Rapine and Tyranny as had torn her from his Boſom. That as he had contracted himſelf her very Husband, and only waited an Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Death; why not ſome little Anticipation of his rightful Joys, and not ſo tedious an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance only for the Reverſion of Felicity? Why ſhould they poſtpone that Happineſs to long long Years to come; poſſibly a whole Age diſtant, when the preſent Golden Minute ſmiled before 'em? Nay, granting ſome ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Fault, a Weakneſs, or Frailty, in the Conceſſion; which either her too nice Virtue, or ſcrupulous Fears might raiſe againſt him; however, taking the whole heap of their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated Wrongs together, nothing ſure cou'd be more excuſable than <hi>Peregrine</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi> A great many other Arguments he urged, which were all anſwer'd by the invincible Virtue of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi> The chiefeſt Objection was the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of an offended Heaven, which ſhe durſt not incurr; ſhe trembled but at the very Thought of the broken Sleeps and diſtracted Peace, that the violation of her Virtue would undoubtedly pull down upon her, telling him, That he ought to content himſelf with the Favours (even to a Profuſeneſs) ſhe had already granted him, and wait the pleaſure of Providence, which one Day might more amply crown his Joys. She beſought him to take it as ſome additional Favour too, that ſhe could hear him urge ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48097:30"/>immodeſt and unreaſonable a Petition, with ſo much Patience and Forgiveneſs, for ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be angry even at an offending <hi>Peregrine.</hi> Nay, (throwing her white Arms about his Neck) my dear, dear, <hi>Peregrine,</hi> ſhe cried; think what 'tis you Ask and what I muſt Deny. For believe me, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Heart is moulded all of the ſame Love as <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and I give you leave to think, there is not that warmeſt Wiſh, his melting Soul can form, but is met, returned and anſwer'd by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania.</hi> She deſired him then to reſt ſatisfied that nothing but her Honour, which ſhe muſt never Violate, held the Flaming-ſword that barr'd both His Paradice and Hers. And after all this frank Confeſſion, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured him by all that's Sacred to deſiſt from that Suit which ſhe hears with a Pain, denies with a greater; and yet the Grant were the greateſt, under the pangs of a bleeding Virtue, and therefore muſt be denied. The amorous <hi>Peregrine,</hi> in all the Raptures of this generous Confeſſion, was contented to ceaſe the Subject, at leaſt for the preſent. But upon ſeveral Meetings afterwards, the Subject was revived: But not to particularize the whole Arguments on both ſides, let it ſuffice, that he wrought that impreſſion upon the yeilding <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> that at laſt ſhe confeſt, that both Virtue and Honour were ſtormed and vanquiſh'd, and nothing but the exceſs of her very Love refuſed him; that laſt impregnable Retrenchment againſt him. How, Love! Anſwered the amaz'd <hi>Peregrine.</hi> Yes, Love, replied the ſighing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> I Love
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48097:30"/>ſo well, that I neither dare make my ſelf nor my <hi>Peregrine</hi> happy; for from that Hour my tottering Virtue ſhakes, as proudly as my <hi>Peregrine</hi> may wear the preſent Trophy, yet if that Day ſhould come, when my Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Death, and my happy Widowhood might open my lawful Arms to his Embraces, he would then look back upon the cheap Favours I had given him, and under the common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of that eaſy Creature a Wanton, ſtart from ſo poor and ſo diſhonour'd a Thing, and diſdain ſo low-priz'd a Bliſs as the Arms of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> for his honourable bridal Joys. In ſhort, ſhe told him ſhe loved to ſuch a height, that the ties of her Favours muſt be a Seal for Life, and therefore ſhe dares not be guilty of a Weakneſs that may hazard even the remoteſt Loſs of her <hi>Peregrine,</hi> though for all the moſt exalted Felicities that his utmoſt Love can give her. For ſhe cannot think of living Bleſt in his Arms, without being ſecure of dying Bleſt there too. And for that, and indeed that only Reaſon, ſhe muſt deny him.</p>
               <p>This laſt generous Argument, was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately as generouſly anſwered by the paſſionate <hi>Peregrine;</hi> who told her, their Caſe was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly different from the common Breaches of the Marriage-bed; or indeed was rather no Breach at all. The whole true Right was in the Lover, not the Husband. That though, its true, it was always reputed not only an ignoble, but a hazardous Condeſcenſion in a Man of Honour, to Marry thoſe eaſy Fools, that before Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48097:31"/>would be ſo weak as to yeild their cheap unlicenſed Favours, and much more thoſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine Rovers, that could break through the ſacred Bonds of Matrimony; as too dangerous truſting to ſuch brittle Bridal Fidelity. But his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Condeſcenſion on the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary was rather a conjugal Conſummation than Violation: That nothing but invincible Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had raviſh'd her from him; that he ſhould eſteem her Conceſſions as not the leaſt Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Juſtice, no leſs on that very ſacred Conſummation; and be ſo far from refuſing her a formal Marriage, when the Death of her Tyrant ſhould entitule him to that Ceremony, that he ſhould think himſelf an abſolute Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate both from Love and Honour at the very thought of ſuch a Refuſal. In fine, he had ſo much to ſay upon this copious Subject, and bound it all with ſo many Oaths of eternal Truth and inſeparable Bonds between 'em, that even that laſt impregnable Retrenchment can hold out no longer.</p>
               <p>And now for the happy <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s Inſtalment in the Throne of Love, or rather his tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Immortality; (for Empire and Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe are both in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Arms, and no Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Bliſs can expreſs his Felicity) firſt there's a ſolemn <hi>Pacta Conventa</hi> Sworn on his part, of no leſs Contract and Obligation than a Seal for Life. And then for the Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the happy Lovers, 'tis agreed on the Ladies ſide, that ſhe'll find an Excuſe to be abſent the whole Day to Morrow from Seven
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48097:31"/>in the Morning till Ten at Night; againſt which time the amorous <hi>Peregrine</hi> engages to provide a Bridal-Bed (for that's the Name he gives it) not at his own Houſe, for the Ladies Honour muſt be guarded; and not any of his Servants muſt be truſted with ſo important a Secret: And therefore he provides a Chamber very richly Furniſh'd in the <hi>Middle Temple,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lady convey'd by Water, in a Diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee and a Mask, is received at the <hi>Temple</hi>-ſtairs by the waiting <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and handed up to the Palace of <hi>Cupid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here ſhe finds a Bed-chamber and a Bed all richly Perſumed, a Table ſpread in the Dining Room with great variety of Rarieties, but all cold Diſhes, Flasks of rich Wine, and a Pile of Sweetmeats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that's the leaſt part of the Feaſt: No 'tis <hi>Love,</hi> his Nectar and Ambroſia, the Regale of Gods, muſt furniſh this Banquet. 'Tis true, they were a little ſtinted in one part of the hymeneal Ceremony: What other Pomp and State was not wanting, yet ſtill here were no Bride-maids to diſmantle the Bride. And here a little amorous Conteſt aroſe between 'em: The bluſhing <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> ſhe by all means deſired the permiſſion of undreſſing her ſelf; but <hi>Peregrine</hi> he was for ſupplying both the Bride-maid and the Bridegroom, making a Hundred paſſionate Intreaties to have the Charm of diſrobing his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> or rather unclouding his dear Divinity: For ſo he was pleaſed to call it. At laſt the ſupplicating <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrine</hi> prevail'd, that that favour ſhould be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48097:32"/>granted him; the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> yeilding only in this Point, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe came to his Arms as a Wife not a Miſtreſs; and therefore her part was Submiſſion and Duty, and he the Lord of her Love and her Life, 'twas his part to Command and be Obey'd: All ſhe beg'd of him, was, that he would be ſo kind even to her Modeſty, as not to exceed the Liberties of a Bride-maid, or offer the leaſt Indecencies that might put her to a feminine Bluſh: For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Bluſhes ſhe might afterwards receive in his Arms, those ſhe would hide in his Boſom. The generous <hi>Peregrine</hi> conceded this Point, and promiſed her faithfully he would not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the Limits preſcribed, but act the very Virgin Bride-maid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But oh, when he came to perform the Virgin Office; (for, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the aforeſaid Articles, ſhe ſubmitted her whole Diſ-robement to his Hand) when by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, nearer and nearer, and all with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand new diſcover'd Beauties, he had unveild her almoſt to her naked Charms, Gods! what a check, what a reſtraint was it to be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Peregrine,</hi> now all on fire, to ſee the repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Eye of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> (for all the while he undreſt her, ſhe aw'd him with that Look as reminded him that he was yet but a Bride-maid) debar him even the leaſt preliminary Freedom, though not three Minutes diſtant from the moſt unbounded exalted Felicities.</p>
               <p>When he had put her to Bed, and ſcarce a Minutes time had thrown him into her Arms, (for his Joys, were too Rapid to make much Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony in undreſſing himſelf) Oh! in what a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48097:32"/>Torrent of Bliſſes, did melting Love pour forth his higheſt Raptures! In ſhort, I can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell my Reader, That ſuch were the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, even of one ſhort Minute, as if they reſolved the Joy of an Hour ſhould repay the Sighs of an Age; and the long-ſuffering Years behind 'em be utterly forgotten. In theſe, I may ſay, almoſt continued Extaſies between 'em (for the very Intervals of Rapture had ſo much Endearment as wanted but very few degrees, even of the higheſt Beatitude) they continued till Noon: At which time by a conſenting Parly between the Amorous Combitants, it was agreed on both ſides, they ſhould Furle up the Colours, give a Ceſſation of Arms, and quit the Field for ſhort Quarters of Refreſhment.</p>
               <p>Accordingly they each of them ſlipt on a Night Gown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and retired into the Dining Room, where they made a ſhort Repaſt, tho' indeed a double Banquet. For the grateful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their late mutual Joys carried ſo charming a Thought with it, that whether they Eat or Drank, ſtill at the ſame time they feaſted their very Eyes too, ſo many languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glances, and dying Looks there paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em; for whilſt their Lips were now other wiſe employ'd, they continued the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Love at their Eyes.</p>
               <p>After this ſhort Ceſſation of Arms, or rather Recruits for new Forces, they both returned to their Colours, <hi>viz.</hi> to Bed again; where we'll leave 'em Engaging and Rallying, with all the open Arms and utmoſt Efforts of Love, till
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48097:33"/>about Nine at Night; at which time making a drawn Battle between 'em, the Amorous and now Fatigu'd Combatants retired, having made a new Challenge of another ſelect Day of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame Quarrel.</p>
               <p>After this mutual Conqueſt (for both ſides come off Victors in the Battles of Love) I will not enlarge upon this part of my Hiſtory any more, than to tell my Reader, That the happy Pair very often met, and the Scene of Felicity, always the ſame Chamber in the <hi>Temple,</hi> where the ſeveral Meetings were little leſs than ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new Bridals; for they Loved at that rate both of Ardour and Conſtancy, that Length of Enjoyment put out no Spark of the Fire.</p>
               <p>In a very little time after, the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to have ſome very apparent or rather Preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Symptoms, of her fulfilling the <hi>Firſt,</hi> (how much ſoever the nicer Caſuiſts may accuſe her of breaking one of the other Commandments) <hi>viz.</hi> That Original great Work of her Creation, <hi>Increaſe and Multiply;</hi> for ſhe was pretty far gon with Child. At this time Summer coming on, ſhe went up to her Country-Houſe at <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> where the greateſt part of the Week (as much as his Abſence from <hi>Change</hi> would permit) ſhe was Viſited and Attended by her Half-Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow, (though Heaven knows not Quarter-ſharer) her fond Cit.</p>
               <p>At this Place ſhe mannag'd a Project of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting an Acquaintance between her Knight and her Baronet. For the Knight being a great Bowler, it was reſolved that her <hi>Peregrine</hi> ſhould
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48097:33"/>amongſt the other crowd of Gentry, come down to <hi>Richmond;</hi> and by being a conſtant Gameſter at the Bowling-green, ſhould ſcrew himſelf into a particular Familiarity with the Husband, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſucceeded to their Whiſhes. For the Baronet took ſeveral occaſions of Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging the Knight at <hi>Rub and a good Caſt;</hi> nay, very often play'd Booty, on purpoſe to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his winning Hand; which begot ſuch a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity between 'em, that the Baronet was ſoon made an invited Gueſt to his Houſe: Which Admiſſion gain'd the Point.</p>
               <p>This Initiation of a Country Friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, opened a fair Door for his City Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance too: Which gave him occaſion of many publick Viſits; in all which, however our young Lovers managed their Looks and Civilities ſo, as to give no ſhadow of Jealouſie.</p>
               <p>Not long after, the joyful Knight was ſaluted the Father (a Titular one) of a young Squire, a Son and Heir, to his no ſmall Pride; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome little City Honour. For though, 'tis true, he had ſeveral Daughters by his firſt Lady, However this was the Firſt-born Male Iſſue; which gain'd him perhaps a Reputation of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Proweſs among the kind well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Goſſips, to be the Father of ſo luſty a Boy at his Years.</p>
               <p>The Fair young Teemer, the Mother of this young Templar (for ſo I may venture to call him) in leſs than another Year, brought forth another Branch of the ſame fair Fruit-full Stock, a young Daughter. At her upriſing from this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48097:34"/>laſt Labour, it happened that ſhe was invited by her Father down to <hi>Salisbury,</hi> to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a marry'd Siſter of hers, that at that time was juſt upon lying In of her firſt Child, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Married to a Gentleman of conſiderable Fortunes there. Though ſhe could not well refuſe ſuch an Invitation from ſo near and dear a Relation; yet it was with ſome Regret that ſhe muſt be ſeparated from her much dearer <hi>Peregrine,</hi> for at leaſt 6 or 8 Weeks, (for ſhe could not well propoſe to return much ſooner.) Before her departure, ſhe took her leave of her dear <hi>Peregrine</hi> at his Temple-chamber, and could not forbear a ſtream of Tears on ſo melancholy an Account, even in the very warmeſt Arms of Love. However, it gave them an occaſion of renewing their former Vows of eternal Fidelity, it being mutually engaged between 'em, that this Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be only a continued mourning time of Widowhood, till Love ſhall reſtore them to each others Arms.</p>
               <p>The fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> was no ſooner ſet forwards for <hi>Salisbury,</hi> but our City Knight had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Gueſt, his eldeſt Daughter, (bred up at a rich Aunts at <hi>Norwich</hi>) that came up to <hi>London.</hi> This young fair One, was Miſtreſs of a more than common Portion of Beauty, an extraordinary ſweat Creature, about the Age of Seventeen: And though her coming to Town, unſent for, was a little ſurprize to the Father, yet ſuch a Darling of his Heart could never be Unwelcome. The true Cauſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48097:34"/>of her coming was indeed the common Cauſe of the Young and Fair, <hi>viz. <hi>Love.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe lovely Eyes had Charm'd the Heart of a young Country Gentleman of ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds a Year, though poſſibly, at a <hi>Smithfield</hi> Bargain, not altogether full weighty enough, in the Worldly Ballance, anſwerable to what her Father was able, or indeed deſign'd to give her. Theſe fair Eyes had not only darted Flames into this young Gentlemans Heart, but as generouſly receiv'd ſome little Sparks of the ſame Wild-fire into her own; for here was <hi>Love</hi> for <hi>Love,</hi> between 'em, the young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy having contracted a very paſſionate Eſteem for him: And to tell Truth, ſhe had in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtoln up to Town, (her Lover being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe come up with her) on purpoſe to watch the opportunity, under the Smiles of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Father, of introducing him as her profeſt humble Servant, and ſmoothing all the way poſſible to a happy nuptial Knot between 'em.</p>
               <p>As this young Daughter arrived in the abſence of her young Mohter-in-law (whom yet ſhe had not ſeen) it happen'd at that time that <hi>Peregrine</hi> came to Viſit the worſhipful Knight her Father. For though his dear <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> the fair Charmer, that drew him to the Houſe, was gone; however, in Prudence or rather Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he continued his conſtant Viſits there; it being ſuppoſed, inded by the whole Family, that the Friendſhip of the Knight, not the Love of the Lady was the foundation of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48097:35"/>Acquaintance, and which a Ceſſation of his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Civility, might have render'd a matter of Wonder, if not worſe, Suſpicion.</p>
               <p>I dare not ſay what capricious Planet reign'd, that the unfortunate <hi>Peregrine</hi> diſcover'd ſome extraordinary Attractions both in the Perſon, Air, Wit, and whole Converſation of the ſweet <hi>Angeline</hi> (for ſo we'll name her) not only to a common Admiration, but to a little yet nearer Touch: For he not only ſaw ſuch Charms in her Eyes, but felt 'em too. And what contributed to his dayly growing Pain, who ſhould the Knight chooſe out, to uſher her to the Park, the Plays, the Muſick-meetings, and indeed the whole Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Town; but Sir <hi>Peregrine?</hi> The young Lady had had her whole Nurſery in the Country, and therefore muſt be treated with all the Diverſions of <hi>London;</hi> and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded round only by Sir <hi>Peregrine;</hi> ſo intire a Confidence he repoſed in a Man of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and conſequently truſts his beſt Jewel in his Hands.</p>
               <p>This daily and almoſt hourly Poſt of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to attend the fair <hi>Angeline,</hi> in a little time put him upon a very tormenting Rack; he found himſelf gone almoſt before he felt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf going, now not only ſtagger'd but Faln; Not but ſo loſt had been otherwiſe a Pleaſure and Delight: But now his Bed of Roſes, the Charms of the fair <hi>Angeline,</hi> has too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pricking Thorns; when Ingratitude and Infidelity ſtare him in the Face, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48097:35"/>of the wrong'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> ſtrikes both a ſhame and terrour to his Soul.</p>
               <p>His Reſentments of this laſt Barbarity had gon a great way towards the recalling his wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Reaſon, and repairing th Breaches theſe fair Eyes had made through his Truth, Vows and Honour. But another more ſpightful Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief ſtarted up, which was, That at this time he had ſome honourable Relations come to Town, who dayly and hourly teized and tired him with the Invitations of Marriage, urging that great Argument, the Preſervation of his very Name; for without Heirs, his whole E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Honour devolved into another Name and Family, a Collateral half Blood, the next Relation to both of 'em. Nay, ſome of the bolder of his Friends preſt him ſo far, as to tell him plainly, They much feared, he play'd the private Libertine, and his refuſals of ſuch Virtuous Counſel muſt proceed from ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret darling Vice; the cheriſhing of which, would end in his double Ruin, both here and hereafter. In ſhort, betwixt Preaching and Adviſing, Intreaties and Perſwaſions, he was at laſt ſo worried of all ſides, that what with the irreſiſtible Charms of his new Conqueror, he began to liſten to the Enchantment. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd too with himſelf the diſtance and hazard, and uncertain Lottery of all his Hopes of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> the Diſparity of his Own and her Husbands Years, being no true Enſurance of Life; his Youth and the others Age being in the Hands of an inſcrutable Power: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48097:36"/>whatever gawdy Viſions of Innocence the flatteries of Love might fancy in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licenſed Embraces of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> 'twas much to be feared, when weighed in a higher Ballance, that Flattery would be found too light; for whatever Severity of Providence it appear'd to have that deluded Sweetneſs betray'd into ſuch a fatal Wedlock; yet ſuch was the Decree of Providence, and the great Diſpenſer was Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute. And therefore in the Divine as well Humane Canons of Marriage, <hi>Quod fieri non debet, factum valet;</hi> and Marriage whether a Fetter or a Bracelet, is ſtill a Bond; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently his happieſt Embraces were all but ſo many Criminal Violations of Honour.</p>
               <p>Theſe and a hundred Reflections being made, his new Conquerour carried the Cauſe, and in ſhort, he very boldly makes honourable Love to the fair <hi>Angeline.</hi> The young Lady was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtartled at ſuch an humble Servant, and how cold ſoever were her Denials, like Wind to Fire they only enflam'd him the more; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering here muſt be Expedition in the Caſe before <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s return; To make quicker Work of it, he Attack'd the Father, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to ſettle a very large Joynture, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit all pretenſions to a Portion with her. The Father who indeed, deſired no better a Son-in-Law, and perhaps had contracted this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Converſation betwixt his Daughter and him, partly from ſuch ſome hopes; very readily liſten'd to ſo honourable a Profeſſour, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately lay'd his abſolute Commands upon
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48097:36"/>his Daughter to Embrace the Happineſs of ſuch a Husband. The poor Lady was almoſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Afflicted at that Command; for whatever Deſert ſhe might otherwiſe have found in ſuch a Lover, yet here was a Heart already diſpoſed, and conſequently not in her Power to recall.</p>
               <p>The young Country Rival had at this time made ſome Tenders to the Knight a a Suitor to the fair <hi>Angeline,</hi> and the Lady ſeem'd inclinable to him; (for 'twas agreed between 'em not to own any Pre engagement, fearing it might breed ill Blood, and be interpreted an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his paternal Authority, in daring to contract Love, and the Father not called to the Conſult.) But whatever Inclinations the Father might otherwiſe have had towards this Country Pretender, from that Minute that <hi>Peregrine</hi> ſet up for an Addreſſor, he would not ſo much as hear him Named. The whole Dead weight was on this ſide, and the Baronet intirely weigh'd down the Squire; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis reſolved, that nothing but Sir <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi> muſt, and ſhall be the favour'd Lover, the Husband Elect; and conſequently the fair <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> is bid to prepare without any diſpute for a Ladyſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The poor Lady in this Diſtreſs, endeavour'd all that was poſſible to Fence and Sheild againſt this impending Storm: She beg'd the cruel <hi>Peregrine</hi> with wet Eyes and almoſt bended Knees, to deſiſt his hopeleſs Suit. 'Tis true, ſhe durſt not tell him plainly her Heart was not her own, becauſe ſhe would not, and indeed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48097:37"/>durſt not, truſt a Secret of that Importance to a Rival, as dreading ſome fatal uſe that might be made of it, if told to a reſenting Father. And though the Baronet was otherwiſe a Man of great Honour, yet ſtill as all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilities are thought Lawful in Rivalſhip, ſhe durſt not put ſuch a dangerous Diſcovery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Power.</p>
               <p>All theſe continued Repulſes, could not daunt our bold Lover, who ſtill perſues the flying Fair, being reſolved to puſh on the Siege, as invincible as ſhe ſeem'd to hold out againſt him; till at laſt the young Lady Perſecuted by Love on one Hand, Commands on the other (for Reaſons that the ſequal of our Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will diſcover) received the adoring <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi> with a little kinder Aſpect; nay, made him thoſe advances of her Favour, that in three days more Courtſhip ſhe ſtruck the Flag, and received him as the Conqueror.</p>
               <p>I will not deſcribe the Triumphs the happy <hi>Peregrine</hi> made, upon ſo charming a Victory, the Glory of which was not a little heightned by the oppoſition and obſtinacy he met in his firſt Aſſaults; it is enough to tell you, That the yeilding Lady on her part, to careſs the Man, ſhe has now made happy; having now no reſerves of Coyneſs or Coldneſs, told him very kindly, That it was her Duty now to contribute every thing in her Power to their mutual future Happineſs; and therefore ſhe muſt communicate one extraordinary Secret to him, which was, That her Father, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48097:37"/>ever his outward Aſpect, or rather Diſguiſe to the World might be, was in his Heart, the moſt hearty and unſhaken Zealot for King <hi>James,</hi> poſſibly in the Kingdom: That as her <hi>Peregrine</hi> (for now ſhe'll call him ſo) was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a Favourite ſo near his Boſom, and in a little time might be yet nearer, ſhe thought that nothing could be more adviſeable for him, than to take ſome private opportunity of careſſing her Father upon that Subject; for as much as her Father already Loved and Honour'd him, there could be no exceſs in Love: And it would only make the Bonds the more inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the approaching Alliance yet more grateful, if he ſhould let drop any Expreſſions of his own Inclinations that way, to tranſport him with that new Satisfaction and Pleaſure, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was like to have a Son-in-Law of his own Principle and Conſtitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The kind <hi>Peregrine</hi> received this generous Information with a hundred Thanks, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed there ſhould be ſought a very ſpeedy opportunity of obeying her Commands. 'Tis true, as he might open his Soul to his dear <hi>Angeline,</hi> he confeſt, that his Pulſe beat very little that way; However, that was but a civil Complaiſance to ſtrain a Point, upon ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant an Account as the endearing in all kinds a Perſon, whom he had ſo many Obligations of the higheſt Duty to Reſpect and Honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peregrine,</hi> who very wiſely, was for imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt ſmiling Minute that offer'd ſo fair for Happineſs, immediately attended the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48097:38"/>Knight, with ſome <hi>Io peans</hi> of his Conqueſt, and then deſired his permiſſion of engaging his Lawyer with the firſt expedition of drawing the Joynture; all which you may imagine was gratefully accepted and granted by the Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Don Senior.</hi> And the very next Night the Baronets gay Coach and Livery were order'd to attend the Aldermans Door, to invite him forth to his Man of Law at his Chambers in the new Square in <hi>Gray</hi>'s-Inn; where coming about 20 Minutes before the Hour appointed, the Clerk received them with a great deal of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, told them his Maſter was ready with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in call, at another Brothers of the Robe in the Inn, from whence he was commanded to call him; and therefore deſired their Pardon for a Moments Patience, till he could fetch his Maſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peregrine</hi> now remembring his dear <hi>Angeline</hi>'s laſt Commands, and this being the firſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opportunity, himſelf and the Knight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then all alone in a large Chamber, began firſt to tell him how Bleſt he ſhould be in the Embraces of ſo charming a Creature as the fair <hi>Angeline,</hi> and not only ſo but doubly Bleſt in the Alliance to a Family of ſuch true Worth and Virtue.</p>
               <p>For Sir, continued her, believe me 'tis no little pleaſure to my Soul to think that this happy Knot will tye me ſo near to a Perſon of that more than common Merit and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, that his Loyalty ſhines equal, nay, if poſſible, beyond his other Virtues. My Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty!
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48097:38"/>reply'd the Alderman. Yes Sir (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted he) I know you honour our great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, are a true and pious Mourner for his Wrongs; and if the Infinite Goodneſs would but graciouſly pleaſe to withdraw his too long Indignation that hangs Louring o'er theſe poor Kingdoms, and reſtore our dear Prince to his Throne—Lord Sir, anſwer'd the Knight, what do you mean! (holding up his Hands in an Amazement:) Nay Sir, reply'd the Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, I ſee you are ſurpriz'd, I know I have crept into the ſecrets of your Heart; but never doubt your ever obedient humble Servant; my Silence ſhall keep a very faithful Key to ſo rich a Cabinet. And to ſecure you, my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery ſhall never turn to your prejudice in ſo ſacred a Truſt: I beſeech you to reſt ſatisfied that I am as nearly related to your Virtues, at leaſt in that Point, as I hope I ſhall be to your Blood. For to deal plainly with you, not to be vain of what's no more than my Duty; there is not that honeſt Subject in the Nation, more in the Intereſts of that unfortunate Prince than my ſelf; and when that bleſſed Day ſhall come when I may ſhew the World—Here Mr. Lawyer came in, and broke off the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; when the Baronet calling for the Writings, they were immediately brought out of his Cloſet, all ready for Signing and Seal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>When the Writings were produced, the firſt Word the Knight Spoke was to ask the Lawyer, what the Writings muſt coſt.—
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48097:39"/>Coſt! Sir, anſwered the Son Elect, a little amaz'd. Ay Coſt! (ſays the Don) the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of 'em I mean: I ſuppoſe Mr. Lawyer muſt have his Fee; Law and Goſpel are both Goods and Chattels that muſt be Bought and Pay'd for, as Juſtice and Divinity go now. The Knight ſtill preſt the Lawyer to tell him what he muſt have for the Writings; for no Man ſhall pay for 'em but himſelf.—<hi>Per.</hi> Lord bleſs me Sir! What do you mean?—Kt. <hi>Lord bleſs us all, for 'tis a very wicked World we now live in. Once more Mr. Lawyer, what muſt I pay you? Lawy.</hi> Nay Sir, ſince 'tis your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I deſerve Five Pounds.—Kt. <hi>Let every Man have his Deſerts, I ſay, and give the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows her due.—There's your Mony</hi> (throwing down five Guineas.) <hi>And here's your Joynture</hi> (throwing it upon the Fire, and ſtamping his Foot upon it.) <hi>Marry my Daughter to a Son of</hi> Belial, <hi>a</hi> Tory, <hi>a</hi> Rapparee, <hi>a</hi> Jacobite! <hi>What do you ſee in my Face! And what have I ſeen in yours, to be thus long deluded? What a falſe Snake have I all this while lodged in my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom! Look you Sir</hi> Peregrine, <hi>or Sir Monſter, which is your properer Title, I defy your</hi> Devil, <hi>your</hi> Pope, <hi>your</hi> French King, <hi>and all their Works: And henceforward pray take care to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your great Jacobite Leader, and abdicate my Houſe and Family; for I am a Magiſtrate, an Alderman, and a Juſtice of the Peace; and I ſhall make bold to tell you, My Roof harbours no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels; and there's a great Houſe near</hi> Snow-Hill <hi>fitter for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:48097:39"/>
               <p>The poor <hi>Peregrine</hi> was abſolutely Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck at all this irruption of Fire and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and could hardly return a word; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Alderman ſtop'd his Mouth, for he would hear nothing. And ſo bolting out of the Room, with his Hands up to Heaven, and this ſhort Ejaculation, <hi>From Sedition, Conſpiracy and Rebellion, good Lord deliver us;</hi> he called a Hackney Coach, and drove home like a <hi>Jehu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The very firſt Out-cry he made, was to call his dear <hi>Angeline,</hi> and to tell her the whole Story; what a Deliverance ſhe had, and what Ruin ſhe had eſcaped. The poor Lady fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Knees, and thanked Heaven for her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: And juſt in the height of his whole Triumph for ſo happy a Diſcovery of the Cloven-foot, the Fiend, the Lucifer, the Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, and what not! Who ſhould luckily enter, but the poor diſcarded <hi>Norfolk</hi> Squire, who laying hold of ſo favourable a Minute, renew'd his Addreſſes of Love with that ſucceſs, that before they parted, the old Spark very frankly received him into Favour, and admitted him a Servant to his Daughter; and in three Days time the Planets of Love ſo ſmil'd upon them, that Portion, Settlement, Joynture, and the whole Match was concluded to the young Couple's no little Satisfaction, and no common Joys between 'em.</p>
               <p>The very next Day the fair (I may ſay) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgotten Traveller, return'd from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Her firſt Entertainment, after a conjugal
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48097:40"/>Salutation from her Knight, and the Embraces of her fair Daughter-in-Law, was the whole Story at full length of Sir <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s Defeat, and the fair <hi>Angeline</hi>'s Triumph. The poor Lady was ready to ſink Dead at the Relation; which the Alderman obſerving, the Lady ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed her change of Colour by telling him, She did not believe there could be ſuch Incarnate Devils in the World; and was ſorry to think a Man of ſuch profeſt Honour as Sir <hi>Peregrine,</hi> ſhould be ſuch a Monſter. This encouraged the Knight to finiſh the whole Narrative, which you may imagine was ſet forth in the blackeſt Hew; till the poor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> was forced to feign an Indiſpoſition, to get a little Privacy with her <hi>Fidelia,</hi> (who Travelling with her Lady to <hi>Sarum,</hi> was as great a ſtranger to what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd at <hi>London</hi> as her Miſtreſs) to vent her juſt Reſentments againſt the Infidelity and Apoſtacy of the perjur'd <hi>Peregrine.</hi> I will not deſcribe the Agonies the poor Lady felt at this Occaſion; when juſt at this interim, comes a Meſſenger to <hi>Fidelia</hi> with a Letter from Sir <hi>Peregrine,</hi> who, poor Gentleman, under no little Shame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, deſired the favour of ſpeaking with her at his Lodgings. Her Miſtreſs at firſt, would very hardly conſent to let even a Servant of hers, hold any Correſpondence with ſo much Barbarity, Ingratitude and Falſhood: But her Maid requeſting that favour of hearing what the poor Gentleman had to ſay for himſelf, at laſt ſhe obtain'd her Miſtreſs' leave of calling upon him the morrow Morning.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:48097:40"/>
               <p>In the mean while this very Evening, by a particular Commiſſion from his fair <hi>Angeline,</hi> our young <hi>Norfolk</hi> Lover, was ſent to the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronets Chamber to make a piece of an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the innocent Impoſture ſhe had put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The young Lover found him within, and accordingly beg'd his Excuſe for the Meſſage that the fair <hi>Angeline</hi>'s Commands had enjoyn'd him to deliver. The Baronet very readily lent his Attention, when the Squire as frankly told him his whole Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Contracts with that young Lady at <hi>Norwich;</hi> and though otherwiſe he had all the Reaſon in the World to dread ſo formidable a Rival as the honourable Sir <hi>Peregrine;</hi> yet the fair <hi>Angeline</hi> being all Truth and Virtue, 'twas to that only Obligation he owed the Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of her Heart, and the approaching Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities he was now going to receive in her Bridal Embraces: However, ſhe had a little Trouble and Shame lay upon her, to think how ſhe had been forced to ſuch a piece of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine Artifice and Deluſion impoſed upon a Perſon of ſuch Deſert as Sir <hi>Peregrine;</hi> never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, ſhe beſought his Pardon for a Fault, ſo much the more Venial, as being really no other than a Stratagem of <hi>Virtue,</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Cruelty of a commanding Father, and to Fence againſt ſo powerful an Invader as Sir <hi>Peregrine.</hi> In ſhort, 'twas in the Cauſe of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> and if there could be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Fraud, ſhe hoped he would excuſe it as ſuch; deſiring him to believe, That ſhe ſhould
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48097:41"/>ever carry a very great Eſteem and Veneration for a Perſon of his Quality, that had honour'd her with that Love which ſhe was no ways worthy of, and which ſhe hoped would ſoon find a fairer and more deſerving Object.— The Baronet very civilly returned Anſwer, That the young Lady was highly commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for that Cardinal Virtue <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH</hi> in <hi>LOVE;</hi> and he heartily wiſh'd he had been as great a Maſter of that Perfection himſelf. As for his part he heartily forgave the fair De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luder, on ſo honourable an Account; and had no Reſentment left againſt her, but only, That ſhe was a little too unkind in ſo far doubting his Honour, as not to dare to truſt him with the ſecret of her Pre-engagement; declaring that if ſhe had given him the leaſt hint of ſuch a Confeſſion, as well in Tenderneſs both to her Peace and Vows, he ſhould have thought himſelf in all Duty Bound, though with never ſo much Pain to himſelf, to deſiſt from ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt a Perſecution. For as much a Jacobite as the Lady had made him; he had a little more Tenderneſs to <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> and more Veneration for <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Contracts,</hi> than to admit of a Diſpenſing Power. And therefore he heartily wiſhes her Joy in the Diſpoſal of her Hand and Heart, by a more rightful Title, to his happy, though never ſo much envy'd, Rival.</p>
               <p>The next Morning <hi>Fidelia</hi> came to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, where (to ſhorten my Story) he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her to be the faithful Meſſenger of his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48097:41"/>whole Pains, Confuſion and Horrours to the wrong'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> relating at full length the whole Perſecution of his tireſome Relations, that had hurried and plung'd him into all this Infidelity: For which he beg'd a thouſand of Pardons, humbly beſeeching the injur'd <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> to make her ſelf the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of her Sex, by a Mercy and Forgiveneſs extended to ſo hainous a Tranſgreſſour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Several other Conferences paſt between <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrine</hi> and <hi>Fidelia,</hi> before his Tears and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence could prevail (in which the kind <hi>Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> was a hearty Interceſſour) to obtain a ſight of the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> which after three Weeks Prayers was granted him. At their meeting the poor <hi>Peregrine</hi> ſo trembled at the ſight of her, and fell into that melting Paſſion, as to even Unman himſelf. The generous <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> not to triumph over a bluſhing Shame, gave him very few Reprimands; only told him it was a degenerate World; and ſhe was Sorry, that there was not a perfect Character in it; <hi>Peregrine</hi> was the Man of the Creation ſhe thought came the neareſt to a Perfection, but there are Spots even in the Sun; and even that <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi> has his Faults. This generous Rebuke toucht him ſo near, and ſo charm'd him, that if poſſible, he diſcover'd new Graces in her Eyes: For whether his Repentance inflamed him to a warmer Devotion; or that the repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Injuries oblig'd him to a treble ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, the ſenſe of his Infidelity only height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Adoration; and never was <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> ſo
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48097:42"/>lovely as now. The Breach in his Faith that the unhappy <hi>Angeline</hi> had made, was now no more than a divided Water, where the Dam was broke down, the Torrents rejoyn'd; and not ſo much as a Mark of the ſeparation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd.</p>
               <p>This the amorous <hi>Peregrine</hi> endeavour'd by an hundred Proteſtations to convince her; and though Proteſtations, ſhe had but too much Reaſon to remember, had been only <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Cords; however, he beſought her to enjoyn him a Pennance though never ſo ſevere, that might waſh him White again; which he would Obey without a Murmur or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute.</p>
               <p>Then reply'd the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> I take you at your Word; from this Hour forward never ask me a forbidden Favour. If you can live contented within the Bounds of Virtue, and make that noble Teſt of your Love, as to quite all Libertine Pretentions whatſoever, I'll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you that paſſionate Convert you profeſs your ſelf, and from this Minute Sign your Pardon. Nor believe 'tis my Cruelty that pronounces this Sentence: No <hi>Peregrine,</hi> 'tis my Kindneſs. Love Innocently, dear <hi>Peregrine,</hi> and be happy; for 'tis they only can hope for Bleſſings who deſerve them. Madam, reply'd the ſighing <hi>Peregrine,</hi> I embrace my Doom; to atone my Ingratitude, and merit my Pardon from you, I'll give you Proofs beyond Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. For from this Day forward, I'll Love my divine <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> for the Glory of Love;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48097:42"/>I'll ſerve without Pay, and run the whole Race of Truth without the Reward. Grant me but now and then a Meeting Eye, and ſometimes a melting Lip, juſt enough to keep a ſtarving Wretch alive; and till the Seal of Heaven ſhall make you mine (for ſure Heavens pitying Ear will hear at laſt) I'll never ask you more. Here the kind <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> pour'd forth a hundred grateful Thanks for ſo noble a Profeſſion; and cheriſh'd her dear <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s virtuous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution with all the tendereſt Arguments ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and now deſired of him her Pardon, as ſhe had granted him his; beg'd him to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the paſt Frailties that ſo bewitching a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer had extorted from her; and look for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to a Beam of that ſmiling Providence, which would one Day amply pay their Patience and their Sufferings.</p>
               <p>To conclude, theſe mutual Articles were Ratified, and as infringibly performed: <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine</hi> continued above half a Year in Town, contenting himſelf with the innocent Viſits of his dear <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> and at laſt the Importunities of his Friends giving him new Solicitations and Troubles upon the old hated Argument, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; to be rid of their tireſome Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, he reſolved to go a Volunteer for <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> a Divorce not a little mourn'd by the tender <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania:</hi> However, as it was all for her ſake, ſhe ſubmitted to the generous Cauſe that carry'd himthither.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Peregrine</hi> made <hi>Glory</hi> his <hi>Angeline,</hi> viz. his new Miſtreſs, and continued Three whole
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48097:43"/>Campaigns without one Return for <hi>England:</hi> In all which time a great many tender Letters paſt between 'em, which was the whole Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leon Food, that both their Loves had now to live upon.</p>
               <p>From this laſt Campaign, inſtead of taking up his Winter Quarters in <hi>Flanders,</hi> he took a Ramble round the Provinces of <hi>Holland,</hi> and viſited the Capital Cities of that High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Common wealth; where his ſhort ſtay at any one Place, not permitting the continuance of Letters from his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> it was ſix Weeks ſince he laſt heard from her; however, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to make himſelf amends by Tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf from the <hi>Brill</hi> to <hi>Harwich,</hi> and give himſelf the Bleſſing of thoſe fair Eyes, after ſo long a Separation.</p>
               <p>Upon the Road near <hi>London,</hi> it was his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to meet a Herſe in great Pomp going down into the Country, the Arms of whoſe Scutcheons he had ſomewhere remembred; his Curioſity therefore led him to enquire of the Black-robed Attendants, whoſe Honourable Remains of Mortality they were, ſo Uſher'd with all this Mourning Cavalcade; to which the Anſwer was made him, 'Twas ſuch a Right Worſhipful deceaſed Merchant and Alderman of the City of <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Corps were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying to <hi>Norwich.</hi> Good Heaven! reply'd the tranſported <hi>Peregrine,</hi> in an extaſie to himſelf, the Husband of <hi>Vrania!</hi> Is the Uſurper, the Tyrant Dead! In fine, this ſurprizing News
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48097:43"/>put Spurs to his Horſe, and Wings to his Love to Poſt him to <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Laws of Widowhood were not ſo rigid, but ſuch a Viſitant might gain Admiſſion, even to a Cloſet Mourner: For he took no longer time than to put himſelf into a Funeral Weed, before he viſited the lovely Mourner. I need not tell you how her Mourning became her; but you may eaſily believe that this ruefull Dreſs was the true Habit of Night; for on this Occaſion, to <hi>Peregrines</hi> Eyes, it had all the Stars of the Firmament.</p>
               <p>'Tis much to be ſuſpected that this Viſit of <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s after near three Years Abſence might add a new Current to the wet Eyes of the fair Afflicted, only from a different Fountain, <hi>viz.</hi> Tears of Joy. And truly to do the fair Mourner Right, ſhe divided her reſpective Gratitude to the Living and the Dead; and as far as the decency of her Sable and Cypreſs would permit, ſhe was not wanting in a ſuitable Welcome to ſuch a Viſitant. As for <hi>Peregrine</hi>'s part, he made bold in a very little time to joyn his Compliments of Congratulation with thoſe of Condolence, to Wayle her for what ſhe had loſt, a <hi>Husband;</hi> and Joy her for what ſhe had found, <hi>Liberty.</hi> And now the days of Widowhood move with flow Hours and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sands to the impatient <hi>Peregrine;</hi> he fancies a few Months Diſpenſation might be very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable in her Mourning Ceremony; for to ſay Truth, the fair <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi> her ſelf can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny but the three whole laſt Years have
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48097:44"/>been a ſort of a Widowhood; and indeed the whole conjugal Fires between the Knight and the Lady, her happy <hi>Peregrine</hi> has this pleaſure to believe have burnt but faintly; for he has the ſatisfaction of ſeeing the fair Fruit of her firſt two Years, in a young Heir and Heireſs (<hi>viz.</hi> under his own warm Reign) and a whole Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Field for the three laſt, under the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers colder Adminiſtration. Nay, he could not forbear telling the lovely Widow, That ſhe ought in pure Charity, if only to thoſe two pretty Infants, to throw off her Veil a little ſooner than ordinary; for really it was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regret to him, that theſe two young Pratlers might not call him Father yet. Ah <hi>Peregrine,</hi> reply'd the fair Mourner with half a Smile, thoſe two young Pratlers as you call 'em, may pleaſe You when they call You Father; but by ſome very ſhrewd Signs in their Faces, I fear they'll ſhame Me when they call You ſo. In ſine, the languiſhing <hi>Peregrine</hi> had ſo many Turtle murmurs to make at the ſlow Approaches of his long wiſh'd Felicity, that the poor Lady was forced to take him to Mercy in the half way Stage, <hi>viz.</hi> in bare ſix Months Widowhood; when the now truly and compleatly happy <hi>Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine,</hi> fulfills all his Vows in the conſecrated Knot, the bridal Embraces of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> and Poſſeſſes the whole Joys of Life, in Loves fair Bed of Honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:48097:44"/>
               <head>INTRIEGUE IV.</head>
               <p>A young ſpruce <hi>Linnen Draper,</hi> not long ſet up, took a Ramble in a long Vacation as far as <hi>Newberry.</hi> Here he fell in Love with a very pretty young Virgin Gentlewoman; and made all the paſſionate Addreſſes imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Not that the young Girl cou'd have any Averſion to his Perſon; however the Conqueſt was not ſo eaſily to be accompliſh'd, as in that ſhort time his Buſineſs in <hi>London</hi> wou'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his ſtay in the Country; beſides there were Friends in the Caſe, who muſt now be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too, in his more ſubſtantial Merit, than that of his outward Appearance, to carry ſuch a Beauty, and ſuch a Fortune.</p>
               <p>Being forced up to Town, he continued his Addreſſes by very ingenious Letters twice or thrice a Week, for near four Months; in which her Relations having duly inquired into his worldly Capacities, and the young Lady ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly delighed with ſuch eloquent Black and White, having entertain'd a very tender Thought for him; the Marriage was ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſummated, and the Lady ſeated a fair Citizen's Wife in a very rich Shop in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:48097:45"/>
               <p>This young Bridegroom, contrary to our foregoing Hiſtories, in a manner, kept open Houſe to all the young Beaus of the Town, as being naturally ſo vain of his own perſonal Accompliſhments, (for indeed he was a very handſome Man) that he fear'd no danger from the moſt formidable Rival; and conſequently no Company nor no Entertainments, publick or otherwiſe, were debarred her; rather Priding himſelf in ſo many dayly Viſitants, as he thought cou'd rather prove ſo many envious Spectators, than Invaders of his Felicity, which Thought was his no ſmall Delight and Titilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The young Lady, 'tis true, was a very fond and dutifull Houſhold-dove; not that ſhe wanted a Cage to keep her ſo: Rather the Freedom he allowed her, made a ſtronger im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Love and Confirmation of her Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, according to the true Saying,</p>
               <q>No Obligation binds ſo faſt as Truſt.</q>
               <p>Being a very Airy, Facetious and Ingenious Woman, ſhe was more Charm'd with Wit, than any other Perfection and Converſation, and had made this Obſervation upon her Husband, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſhe thought him much more Eloquent at his Pens-end, than his Tongues; for, reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his Wooing Letters, ſhe thought there was a great deal more Ingenuity in the Air of his Writing, than that of his Diſcourſe, tho' that too was not diſagreeable.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48097:45"/>
               <p>However, as lovingly as they lived together, a Miſchance fell out, that one day prying into a Cloſet, of her Husbands, ſhe found in a ſmall Desk (which through) negligence he had left open) a bundle of Papers tied up together, which her Curioſity inviting her to read, ſhe found 'em all to be the Originals of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Letters to her, and all in a ſtrange Hand, which preſently confirmed her, that all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity that had Conquer'd her, was only a Crutch to a Cripple, an Aſſiſtant Supporter from ſome abler Pen-man's Hand than his own.</p>
               <p>You cannot imagine what a mortifying damp this ſtruck: An hundred untowardly Reflections preſently ſtarted up, not much to his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; to think what notorious Cheats the World was Guilty of; and that a Man who had ſuch a little ſtock of Wit of his own, as ſhe now plainly found he had, ſhould be ſo Impudent as to borrow abroad ſo egregiouſly as he had done. Nay, ſhe could not forbear reflecting, even upon the very Diſcovery it ſelf, as almoſt a greater Crime than the other, concluding it a piece of Folly, of the two the more unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable: For though a Blockhead might bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row help on ſo important an occaſion as the winning a Miſtreſs; yet the keeping thoſe Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, thoſe Teſtimonies and Records of his own Witleſs ſhame, was ſuch incorrigible Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity as not to be match'd.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, from this Diſcovery ſhe conceiv'd ſo poor and deſpicable a Thought of him, (ſuch is the Caprice of Woman) as at laſt grew up
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48097:46"/>to a downright Averſion to him. Not that ſhe publiſh'd her Reſentments, or outwardly made any change in her Converſation, or ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſpect towards him: But this was the more dangerous Rancour, far above any ſuch trivial Womans Anger that vents it ſelf in a few peeviſh Words. No, ſhe began in a manner abſolutely to loath him; and if ſhe forced her ſelf to any Complacence or Civility towards him, 'twas only to carry on a more for midable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, as ſo notorious an Injury ſhe thought de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; for Impoſture and Villany were the moſt favourable names ſhe cou'd give ſo poor a Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinking it the moſt barbarous Impoſition for Woman of her Wit and Senſe to be ſo Snared and Yrapaned into the Embraces of a Fool.</p>
               <p>What Execution this Wedlock Revenge, this Feminine Malice propenſe muſt end in, the Reader may gueſs. For performance of which Revenge Occaſion dayly offer'd, in very plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful choice of Viſitants, all her humble Servants, and none but wou'd have been proud of ſo fair a Lady's Favours, had ſhe but made the leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards the Encouragement of ſuch a Preſumption. However, though ſhe made ſo unlucky a choice of a Husband, ſhe was reſolv'd to be more curious and more cautious in chooſing a Gallant; for if ſhe play'd the Wanton it ſhould be there, where her wants at home (<hi>viz.</hi> Wit and Senſe) cou'd be more amply furniſh'd abroad. Now it happen'd that one bold Spark among the reſt, a frequent Gueſt in the Family, took the opportunity one day to make downright and hearty Love to her, which the Lady (for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48097:46"/>the foregoing Reaſons) not much repremanding, ſhe made anſwer, That truly if ever ſhe vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to confer her good Graces upon any Man, it muſt be where ſhe found Wit as well as other Charms to deſerve 'em; and of which ſhe muſt have very evident Proofs too.</p>
               <p>The young Lover highly pleaſed with ſuch a Declaration, and upon further Harangue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em upon this Text, finding what fort of Abilities in that Faculty would beſt prevail; frankly told her, that if that was the Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to her Favours, he hoped he might ſtand as fair for that Happineſs, as any of his Rivals: for though it did not ſo well become him, to magnify his own Parts, yet ſince he had no other Teſt for his Qualifications to her Smiles, he was the more confident to tell her, he pretended to ſome little Talent of Wit, as being indeed a Brother of the Muſes: For in ſhort he profeſt himſelf a Poet.</p>
               <p>A Poet, reply'd the Lady, mightily pleaſed, Poetry! the only Wit in the World ſhe delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in: She had made it the whole Study of her Youth, having indeed neg lected both the Needle and the Dancing-ſchool, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions and improvement from her <hi>Cowley,</hi> her <hi>Dorinda,</hi> her <hi>Dryden</hi> and what not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In fine, it came to this Iſſue, he ſhould give her Demonſtration in that only Point of Merit, and then truſt to her Goodneſs to reward it.</p>
               <p>Then, Madam, I'll tell you, replies the Spark, not a little elevated with his proſpect of Felicity: I am a Member of the honourable
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48097:47"/>Society of Archers, a fair Regiment upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to grace a Lord Mayors Day. Now we had a good old Knight, a famous Archer, call'd Sir <hi>William Wood,</hi> ſometimes our Servant as the Marſhal of our Company, who lately dying, the Company were pleaſed to give him a very honourable Interment in <hi>Clarkenwell</hi> Church-yard, with three Flights of whiſtling Arrows over his Grave. Nay, reſolving like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to beſtow a Monument upon him too, we ſet a Town Poet, a Fellow that makes it his Bread, to write him an Epitaph; which if you pleaſe, I'll recite you as follows:</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>An Epitaph on Sir <hi>W. Wood.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>HEre just his own Bowes length, e'ne five Foot deep,</l>
                     <l>Does old Sir <hi>W. Wood</hi> take his last Sleep;</l>
                     <l>A Bow-man famous, and a Marks-man bold,</l>
                     <l>As ever hit the conquering Point of Gold:</l>
                     <l>Till that grim Archer, whoſe keen Shaft of Fate,</l>
                     <l>Ne're Shoots but once, but ſtill aims ſure, tho' late;</l>
                     <l>Made both the Targetteer and Target yield,</l>
                     <l>And conquer'd even the Captain of the Field.</l>
                     <l>However, poor Sir <hi>William</hi> ne're repine;</l>
                     <l>Thy Bowe and Quiver with Content reſign.</l>
                     <l>Tho' from Twelveſoore now pent to ſix Foot room;</l>
                     <l>Yet, if thy laſt bold Shot has but reach'd home,</l>
                     <l>And in the Stars thy mounting Soul but ligh't,</l>
                     <l>It is the faireſt Mark thou e're coud'ſt hit.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Now, Madam, continues the young Archer, this inſipid dull Stuff was offer'd us by this Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48097:47"/>Scribler. But, Madam, to ſhew you how much more Acute the Air of a Gentleman is, that Writes for his Diverſion, above a Hireling Scribler; theſe following Lines are of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; <hi>Ex pede Hercules:</hi> But I ſhould not talk Latin to Ladies. By this Sample you'll gueſs at my Poetical Talent.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>SIR <hi>William Wood</hi> lies very near this Stone;</l>
                  <l>In's time, in Archery excell'd by none:</l>
                  <l>Few were his Equals; and that noble Art,</l>
                  <l>Has ſuffer'd now in the moſt tender Part.</l>
                  <l>Long did he Live, the Honour of the Bowe,</l>
                  <l>And his long Life, to that <hi>alone</hi> did owe.</l>
                  <l>But how can Art ſecure, or what can ſave,</l>
                  <l>Extreme old Age, from an appointed Grave?</l>
                  <l>Surviving Archers much his Loſs <hi>lament,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in reſpect, beſtow'd this <hi>Monument:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where whiſtling Arrows did his worth Proclaim,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>eterniz'd</hi> his Memory and Name.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lady.</hi> Well Sir, and this piece of Heroick was a fair Iſſue of yours? <hi>Gent.</hi> All my own I aſſure you. <hi>Lady.</hi> And made choice by the whole Body Corporate for Sir <hi>William</hi>'s Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Gent.</hi> All in Capitals I can aſſure you. But dear Madam your Judgment? <hi>Lady.</hi> Then to tell you my frank Opinion upon it, Your learned Doctors of Archery and my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are quite different. I thank my kind Stars, I never deſire to hear a more Senſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pack of Rhime, (for Poetry I dare not call it) then this Heroical Wit-ſample of yours, as you are pleaſed to Style it: In
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48097:48"/>the firſt place, <hi>[In's time in Archery]</hi> is ſuch a Botch, and <hi>[Lament]</hi> and <hi>[Monument]</hi> two ſuch wretched Tags of Verſe, that a lower Form Boy at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> would be whipt for. Then for [<hi>His owing his long Life</hi> only <hi>to his Bowe</hi>] 'tis next door to Atheiſm. Did nothing but his Bowe (no God ha mercy Providence) preſerve him alive to the Age of Eighty Two? And then did your <hi>whiſtling Arrows eternize his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory?</hi> A very low prized Immortality, if a never dying Name can be purchaſed ſo cheap, as three Flights of School-boys Arrows. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in my little Senſe, <hi>Immortal Names</hi> are obtained by our own Merits, not by other Folks; and ſo how your Arrows eternized him, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unaccountable. In fine, Sir, your Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Archers have more Pretenſions to the Feather than the Quill; and truly Sir, as to your own Genius in Poetry, 'tis a little Kin to the Head of one of your own Arrows, the Leaden end of it.</p>
               <p>Well, this ſhallow Dabler in <hi>Helicon,</hi> is none of the <hi>Apollo</hi> for her Lute; he has play'd the Sir <hi>Martin,</hi> and marr'd all. But in ſome few Days after, a very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious young Spark, a celebrated Wit, made his Addreſſes with better ſucceſs, whilſt about ten Days Courtſhip carried the Lady. And whatever Titillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether of Revenge or Love, or both together heightned her Raptures, he was ſuch a darling Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, that never was Paſſion, Endearments and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes ſo fond as hers. This Intrigue continued in its full Zenith for about three Months; at which time a young Cozen of hers, a Country Gentleman, near <hi>Newberry,</hi> had a Father dy'd, who left him Heir to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48097:48"/>above a 1000 I <hi>per Annum.</hi> This young Gentleman in his miſerable Fathers days, was bred up more like a Slave, than ſuch an Heir; if he could read Engliſh 'twas all, but he could not write his own Name: And in truth, tho' otherwiſe a comely Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he had no over-great Portion of Senſe, and leſs of Literature. This Cozen had a handſome Siſter with a conſiderable Fortune; now our Lady's own Brother, a Neighbour of this rich Cozen and Heir, (his Country Seat not three Miles off him) made Love to this She-cozen; and to expedite his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, had requeſted his fair City Siſter, to come down into the Country, to be a Spokes-woman for him; ſhe to Court the Brother (for her Fortunes were in his Hands) whilſt he Courted the Siſter, and all to make ſure work in the Match by Ploughing with the fair Heifer. Her Husband he was as fond of ſending down his Wife upon ſuch an Errand, as the Brother cou'd, and immediately lay'd his Commands upon her to poſt away in the Name of <hi>Cupid,</hi> a kind Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to the young Spark on her Brothers behalf.</p>
               <p>The Lady who could no ways refuſe this Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, met her Lover at his Chamber, taking her leave with her kindeſt Embraces, mixt with a Deluge of Tears for this cruel Divorce; complaning moſt pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, to think how ſhe muſt leave ſuch Wit, ſuch charming Converſation, and all that was dear in the World, to go to Court a Fool, a Dunce, an illiterate Blockhead. But 'tis her hard fate, and ſhe muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit; and promiſing him her ſpeedieſt return, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured him to believe ſhe left her Soul behind her; and that the Abſent days ſhe now borrow'd from his Arms, ſhould be repaid with Intereſt; for nothing in the World ſhould be ſo faithful as ſhe, and as nothing ever parted with ſo much Sorrow, ſo nothing ſhould equal the Joys of her return.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:48097:49"/>
               <p>The Lady accordingly ſets forward the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Newberry,</hi> where in leſs than a Fortnights time ſhe ſo gain'd the Aſcendent of the Country Squire, that the Match was concluded, ſolemnized, and what not? However, here was no News of her return; her very Husbands Commands could not drag her back again; ſome Excuſe or another was made to all his Letters, inſomuch that 14 Weeks paſt before ſhe ſaw <hi>London</hi> again. And who ſhould Gallant her to Town, but the Country Squire? The poor Lover at <hi>London,</hi> who had thus long languiſh'd for her, amongſt the reſt of the Congratulators, came to welcome her happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; where the brisk Lady loudly laughing with her Country Cozen, roſe up from her Seat, dropt him a ſhort Courteſie, turn'd him her Cheek for a Salute, and then ſquatted down into her Chair again, to finiſh her Laugh with the Squire. The poor <hi>Celadon</hi> (for that's his Name) was ſtrangely ſurprized at this cold Reception; and it was three Weeks (ſhe was ſo danced abroad by the Squire) before he could obtain one private Word with her: When all ſhe had to ſay, was, That ſhe had bid adieu to all ſuch Vanities, had taken an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atlerable Reſolution of diſpenſing no more Favours; not that any ſcruple of Virtue, or fit of Conſcience (for that particular Queſtion was ask'd her) had been the Cauſe; but ſuch a Reſolution was taken, and never to be retracted: Her Friendſhip was at his Service, but beyond that he muſt expect no more. The poor <hi>Celadon,</hi> tho' otherwiſe Maſter of a great deal of Wit, however was Fool enough to be ſtrangely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at this amazing Change.</p>
               <p>He would not willingly believe the Squire had out rival'd him, the whole gay Humour poſſibly on that ſide being the effect of the late new and nearer Alliance between the Families. Matters held thus, two Months, when Letters came out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from the new Couple, to invite their Siſter down
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:48097:49"/>again, for 6 or 8 Weeks, in the Country; which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was ſo ſeconded by the Cozen, that two Places were taken in the Stage Coach for the Lady and the Squire.—The Day before their Journey a great deal of Company were invited to Dinner to take their Leave, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Amongſt the Crowd, <hi>Celadon</hi> made one; at Dinner the Lady was ſtrangely out of Humour: For her Cozen had been gone a Week down to <hi>Chelmsford</hi> to Viſit a Knight his Relation, and had promiſed her to return three Days ago; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was certain he was come to ſome Miſcheif. Anſwer was made by ſome of the Company, That 'twas but 25 Miles, and the Knight undoubtedly knew of his Journey to Morrow, and would not part with him till the laſt Day he had to ſtay in <hi>London.</hi> All this would not ſatisfy her, for he had promiſed her to be in Town, and 'twas not Knights not Lords could make him break his promiſe with her. <hi>Celadon,</hi> who heard all this had a ſudden Fancy came into his Head, upon which he pretended ſome earneſt Buſineſs, that would hold him half an Hour; at which time he would return to the company, who were pretty for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a chearful Glaſs. He immediately poſted to a Scrivener, and made him write a Letter to the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the Squires Name, to this purpoſe: That by an unhappy fall from his Horſe, between <hi>Chelmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Burntwood,</hi> he had broke his right Arm; that he was under Cure with ſuch a Phyſitian; that he deſired his She-cozen would continue her inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Favour to her Brother and Siſter at <hi>Newberry;</hi> that he doubted not in a very ſhort time to Kiſs her fair Hand, being in the mean time her humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Cripple.</p>
               <p>This he gave to a Porter whom he well pay'd; ordering him to bring it almoſt half a quarter of an Hour after him, and ſay it came up by ſuch a Carrier. <hi>Celadon</hi> immediately poſted back to his Company, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48097:50"/>the Porter came ſoon after him, and gave the Letter as inſtructed. When it was publickly read in the Dining-room, the Lady fell downright raving, <hi>The Villain,</hi> naming the Knights Name, <hi>had made her dear Cozen, drunk; which had thrown him from his Horſe; that he was in his young Blood; 'twould caſt him into a Fever, coſt him his Life, and ſhe ſhould never ſee him more.</hi> The Husband himſelf cry'd out Shame againſt this Extravagant Paſſion, telling her, He himſelf had his Arm broke ten Years ago, and was not Dead yet. No, ſays ſhe. <hi>The Devil can't Kill you;</hi> and ſo bolted away from the Company, and lock'd her ſelf up in her Cloſet; where the Husband (reſenting the Slight ſhe put upon his Friends) broke open the Door, and forced her back again. Here ſhe endeavour'd to compoſe her Books, though Sullen ones; when ſome of he Company, diſcanting upon who ſhould write the Letter, the Lady made Anſwer, <hi>Whoever wrote it, no matter, I am ſure 'tw is of his Dictating, the Style is ſo Witty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She had ſcarcely made anſwer, when the Squire came in, excuſing the reſiſtleſs Command of the <hi>Chelmsford</hi> Knight, who in ſpite of his Promiſe had forcibly detain'd him thus long. He had not time to ſpeak half his Speech, before the Lady had flew into his Arms, and kiſt him over and over, wondering to ſee him ſafe return'd, and all his Bones whole. The Squire was ſtrangely alarmed at this ſalute; but the Letter being produced, it was made a Jeſt to every one round but <hi>Celadon,</hi> who had now unridled all. None in the Company could gueſs at the Author of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but the Lady ſingling out <hi>Celadon,</hi> ſitting alone in the corner of the Room, paſs'd negligently by him, and dropt this Half-whiſper in his Ear, <hi>'Twas you writ this Letter. No, Madam,</hi> reply'd <hi>Celadon, it can be none but your Squires, the Style is ſo Witty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48097:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
